<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of Candia in its ancient and modern state with an account of the siege thereof, begun by the Ottoman Emperour, in the year 1666, continued in 1667 and 1668, and surrendred the latter end of 1669 / the most part collected from private letters, during the siege, sent by one in the service of the republique.</title>
            <author>One in the service of the republique.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1147</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10762</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12277084</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12277084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 625:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of Candia in its ancient and modern state with an account of the siege thereof, begun by the Ottoman Emperour, in the year 1666, continued in 1667 and 1668, and surrendred the latter end of 1669 / the most part collected from private letters, during the siege, sent by one in the service of the republique.</title>
                  <author>One in the service of the republique.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for William Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hērakleion (Greece) --  History --  Siege, 1667-1669.</term>
               <term>Crete (Greece) --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Crete (Greece) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58480:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58480:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DESCRIPTION OF Candia, In its Ancient &amp; Modern State: With an Account of the Siege thereof, Begun by the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperour, in the year 1666, continued in 1667 and 1668, and ſurrendred the latter end of 1669.</p>
            <p>The moſt part Collected from private Letters, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Siege, ſent by one in the ſervice of the Republique.</p>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>Jan.</hi> 4. 1669/70.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>William Crook,</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-bar.</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58480:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58480:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> should not have attempted to trouble you with this Preface, were it not to comply with the Mode of the Times, and partly to fill up a vacant page. This Treatiſe wherewith I preſent you, is a Collection methodiz'd and reduc'd to Form and Order for the Readers advantage; containing an exact deſcription of <hi>Crete,</hi> known now by the general name of <hi>Candia;</hi> with a Relation of the various names of the Place, according to the diverſity of Maſters it hath been ſubject unto; and the Scituation thereof; the fertility and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the Soil; the Nature of the
<pb facs="tcp:58480:3"/>Inhabitants, and their Ancient and Modern both Civil and Eccleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iaſtical Government; together with an account of the Original (though pretended) Cauſe of the Siege; and the Tranſactions, and Military Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits in the year <hi>1666,</hi> when this laſt Siege firſt began; which was continued in <hi>1667</hi> and <hi>1668,</hi> and ſurrendred to the Turk in <hi>1669.</hi> All that I ſhall add is onely this, that here you will finde both variety to divert, and verity to ſatisfie you; ſo that I preſume there will be no cauſe for any perſon to repent of his pains, in the peruſal of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Relation, which hath been ſo long and ſo earnestly deſired by all parties to be ſeen in publick.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="description">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58480:3"/>
            <head>A DESCRIPTION OF Candia.</head>
            <p>IT were altogether inconſiſtent with the truth of our intended <hi>Deſcription</hi> of <hi>Candia,</hi> and would ſwell it to a larger Volume then is deſign'd, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with the various Poetical Fictions and Fabulous Stories of Doting Antiquity, concerning the ſame; as, that it was the Kingdom of <hi>Saturn</hi> in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy of the World; the Birth-place and Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of his Son <hi>Jupiter;</hi> the Seat and Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of <hi>Minas,</hi> and <hi>Rhadamanthus,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58480:4"/>Laws were afterwards imitated in the Prime Cities of <hi>Greece;</hi> and the abode of the luſtful <hi>Paſiphae;</hi> as alſo, that here was the ſo much, celebrated <hi>Labyrinth</hi> made by <hi>Daedalus</hi> for the incloſing and ſecuring the <hi>Minotaure:</hi> nor muſt it be forgotten, ſaith that <hi>Learned Knight,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi>'s Hiſtory of the World.</note> that <hi>Strabo</hi> the Geographer, who flouriſhed in the time of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> was of <hi>Cretan Parents</hi> (though born in the City of <hi>Amaſia</hi> in the Realm of <hi>Pontus</hi>) which adds unto this Iſland as much true renown, as any of the Fictions or Stories (be they what they will) of former times. Therefore we ſhall onely glance upon them where the nature of the Subject requires it, and endeavour to give you an exact compendious account of the Names and Scituation of the Place, the fertility and Commodities of the Soil; the nature of the Inhabitants, and their Ancient as well as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Government: and ſo proceed to the original cauſe of the Siege, and the tranſactions in 1666, 1667, 1668, and part of 1669 till its ſurrender.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Candia</hi> hath in ſeveral Ages, and in ſeveral Authors, obtain'd ſeveral names (as Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> hath obſerv'd.) By <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Euſtathius</hi> it is call'd <hi>Heca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tompolis,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58480:4"/>from the number of one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Cities it then contain'd; but in proces of time, and by the devaſtation of War, they are all ſo deſtroy'd, that the ruines of them are hardly viſible. By <hi>Pliny</hi> and <hi>Solinus, Maca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros,</hi> and <hi>Macaroneſes,</hi> the happy or fortunate Iſland, from the goodneſs of the Soil and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Air. By <hi>Stephanus, Idaea,</hi> from <hi>Ida</hi> a famous Mountain there. By <hi>Giraldus, Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinia,</hi> from the <hi>Telchini</hi> Prieſts of <hi>Cybele</hi> (the Wife of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and Mother of the Gods) who was the principal Goddeſs of this Iſland. The general Name which hath prevailed moſt in all Writers, is that of <hi>Crete,</hi> called <hi>Creta, quaſi Cureta,</hi> by the Figure <hi>Syncope,</hi> from the <hi>Curetes</hi> the Inhabitants hereof, and Prieſts of <hi>Cybele,</hi> ſo called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from their ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or ſhaving of the head: and this ſeems the beſt Etymology; though ſome derive it from <hi>Cretes</hi> the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and others from <hi>Crete</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Heſperus.</hi> At preſent it is known by the name of <hi>Candia,</hi> either <hi>à Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore</hi> from the whiteneſs of the Rocks which encompaſs it, or from <hi>Candia</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Candia</hi> is an Iſland, and according to <hi>Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verius</hi> in his Geography, the largeſt of all the Iſles that are adjacent to <hi>Greece;</hi> being, as <hi>Munſter</hi> and our late Coſmographers write, in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58480:5"/>length 270, in breadth 50, and incompaſs 590 Miles; and ſcituated in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> at ſo equal, a diſtance from <hi>Europe, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> according to Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> as if it were naturally deſign'd to be what <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> calls it, The Lady and Miſtreſs of the Sea; for it is diſtant from <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> now called <hi>Morea,</hi> one hundred Miles; as many from <hi>Aſia minor,</hi> and not above one hundred and fifty from the ſhore of <hi>Africa;</hi> verifying that of <hi>Virgil:</hi>
               <q>Creta Jovis magni medio jacet inſula Ponto.</q>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jove</hi>'s Birth-place <hi>Crete,</hi> a fruitful Land,</l>
                  <l>I'th' middle of the Sea doth ſtand.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Heavenly Bodies, it is ſcituated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the beginning of the fourth Climate, ſo that the longeſt day in a manner is but four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hours and a quarter. It hath on the Eaſt the <hi>Carpathian,</hi> on the Weſt the <hi>Ionian,</hi> on the <hi>North</hi> the <hi>Aegean,</hi> and on the <hi>South</hi> the <hi>African</hi> or <hi>Lybian</hi> Sea. In form it extends Eaſt and Weſt with three Promontories; that towards the Eaſt, called anciently <hi>Samonium,</hi> is now <hi>Capo di Salomone;</hi> that on the South-Weſt looking towards <hi>Africa,</hi> formerly <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maea,</hi> is now name'd <hi>Capo Gabraſſe;</hi> and that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58480:5"/>on the North-Weſt towards <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> of old called <hi>Cunarus,</hi> is now <hi>Capo Cheſtin;</hi> this laſt being oppoſite to <hi>Malta</hi> a <hi>Promontory of Laconia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Soil is very fruitful, eſpecially of thoſe Wines which we call <hi>Muſcadels,</hi> of which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> they tranſport yearly twelve thouſand Butts: this Wine <hi>Munſter</hi> calls <hi>Vinum Malviticum,</hi> ſo nam'd from the Mountain <hi>Malva;</hi> he ſaith it abounds herewith, and hath ſtore of Cypreſs-Trees. There is alſo plenty of <hi>Gums, Honey, Sugar, Olives, Dates, Apples, Oranges, Lemons, Raiſins, Melons, Citrons</hi> and <hi>Pomgranates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many other things at preſent worthy obſervation. Firſt, that this Iſland breeds no Serpent, Venemous, Ravenous, or hurtful Creature; ſo that their Flocks graze ſecurely without a Shepherd. Secondly, if a Woman bites a man ſhrewdly, it is not cured without difficulty; which if true, ſaith the Noble Knight, then the laſt part of the forementioned priviledge, that it breeds no hurtful Creature, muſt be falſe. Thirdly, they have an Herb call'd <hi>Alinios,</hi> which if chewed in the mouth will keep a man from hunger that day. Fourthly, here is beſides many other Phyſical herbs, that called <hi>Dictamnum</hi> or <hi>Dictamnus,</hi> an excellent Antidote againſt Poyſon; which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58480:6"/>is onely peculiar to this Iſland. It af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords alſo great ſtore of <hi>Laudanum,</hi> a Juyce or Gum forced with incredible labour out of a Tree called <hi>Ciſtus,</hi> wherewith the Mountains abound: 'tis a ſoporiferous Medicine, good to create Sheep, if preſcribed according to art.</p>
            <p>The cheifeſt Mountain of note is <hi>Ida,</hi> now <hi>Pſiloriti,</hi> ſcituate in the midſt of the Iſland: here <hi>Jupiter</hi> is fabled to be privately nurſt, and from hence he is called <hi>Idaeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rivers of eminency they have few or none; the principal are <hi>Nilopotamus, Scaſinus, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidnus</hi> and <hi>Vivotro,</hi> towards the North; <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> towards the Eaſt, and <hi>Liniens</hi> towards the Weſt; but none of them are Navigable. The Iſland is very populous, inſomuch that it is thought the <hi>Signiory</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> upon a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den occaſion can raiſe in it ſixty thouſand men able to bear Arms.</p>
            <p>As to the Nature of the people, they have always had the repute of able <hi>Mariners;</hi> they being ſcituated in the midſt of the Sea, having very commodious Harbours and a Fiſh-trade; ſo that when in thoſe times they would tax any perſon for relating an incredible ſtory, they uſed to ſay, <hi>Cretenſis neſcit pelagus;</hi> meaning thereby, that the thing was as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, as for one of <hi>Crete</hi> to be no <hi>Sailer:</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58480:6"/>yet this Virtue or Qualification of theirs was ſtain'd with many notorious Vices, which they yet retain among them, as Malice, Envy and Lying; to which laſt they are ſo addicted, that it grew proverbial to call a horrid Lye <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe mendacium;</hi> and this fault the Poet <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menides</hi> did reprove in them (who was Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of this Iſland) cited by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus, Ch.</hi> 1. <hi>V.</hi> 12.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>
               <l>The <hi>Cretans</hi> always lyars are,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly Beaſts, of labour ſpare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>To which may be added the Latine Proverb, <hi>Cretizare cum Cretenſibus,</hi> To deceive the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, or to be falſe in word and deed: as alſo, that of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> there are three Nations whoſe names begin with the Greek letter K worſe then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocians, Cretans</hi> and <hi>Cilicians;</hi> though ſome apply it to the Cities of <hi>Corinth, Capua</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> beginning all with the ſame letter in that Language; all which were conceiv'd very dangerous to the State of <hi>Rome.</hi> Nor are the <hi>Candians</hi> at this day leſs ſick of their old Diſtemper; for they are as great lyars, and as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58480:7"/>idle as ever they were formerly, and avaricious withal, being very impatient of labour, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to attain any Science perfectly; onely they are good Archers, being accuſtom'd to ſhooting from their youth, and herein thought more dexterous and expert then the <hi>Turks</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>As to their Civil Government, according to <hi>Cluverius</hi> and <hi>Munſter,</hi> it was firſt Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical; they being governed by Kings till <hi>Q. Metellus</hi> did reduce the Iſle (under his power) into a <hi>Province;</hi> and it remain'd under the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinopolitan Emperors,</hi> until the <hi>Saracens</hi> did over-run it with the reſt of <hi>Greece:</hi> but <hi>Baldwinus Earl of Flanders,</hi> and <hi>Emperour of Conſtantinople,</hi> did confer it upon <hi>Boniface Marqueſs of Montferrat;</hi> from whom it was purchaſed by the <hi>Venetians, Anno</hi> 1144, at a vaſt rate, and continued ever ſince under the <hi>Signiory of Venice,</hi> under the name of <hi>Candia,</hi> till in the year 1669 it was ſurrendred to the <hi>Turk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Politie,</hi> they were firſt converted to the Chriſtian Faith by St. <hi>Paul;</hi> who having planted the Goſpel there, left the watering of it to <hi>Titus,</hi> who by him was Conſecrated Biſhop of this Iſle, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending the Churches therein to his care, with power of <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58480:7"/>Cenſure,</hi> as appears clearly by the Text, which proves it belonged to him as their Biſhop, and not as their <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> onely: and this mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly apparent, not onely in the Subſcription of that Epiſtle (according to the mode of writing in thoſe days) where he is ſtiled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The firſt Biſhop of the <hi>Cretan Church;</hi> but alſo by the concurrent Teſtimony of <hi>Euſebius Eccleſ. Hiſt. l.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>S. Ambroſ. in Praeſat. ad Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, S. Hieron. in Titum, c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 5. and in his <hi>Treatiſe de Scriptor. Eccleſiaſt. Theodoret.</hi> quoted by <hi>Oecumenius in Praefat. ad Ep. Tit-Oecumenius</hi> himſelf in <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. and laſtly by <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact.</hi> in his <hi>Preface</hi> to the ſame <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> all which do, <hi>in terminis,</hi> call him <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>the Biſhop of Crete,</hi> agreeable to the uſual ſence of the word <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> in that age, diſtinct from <hi>Presbyter.</hi> This Church whilſt wholly under the Diſcipline of the <hi>Greek Patriarchs,</hi> was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by four <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> and one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Biſhops;</hi> but ſince their ſubjection to the <hi>Republique of Venice,</hi> there is but one <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> that is of <hi>Candia</hi> the chief City; and eight Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, beſides the titular <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> who hath his reſidence there; ſome <hi>Prelate</hi> of the <hi>Latine Church</hi> having been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways honoured with that empty Title, ever ſince the recovery of that City from the <hi>Weſtern Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58480:8"/>
            <p>The Language vulgarly and generally ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken here, is the <hi>Greek Tongue;</hi> though Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Merchants depending on the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> ſpeak <hi>Italian</hi> alſo. Both the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> are uſed in their <hi>Divine Offices:</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple generally are of the Communion of the <hi>Grecian Church;</hi> yet the <hi>Latine Service;</hi> is alſo uſed in many places of the <hi>Iſland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ground of this War between the <hi>Otto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperour</hi> and the <hi>Venetian,</hi> I finde in an Epiſtolar addreſs to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> from <hi>Venice,</hi> by the hand of a <hi>Noble man</hi> of this <hi>Nation</hi> then reſiding there, to be to this effect. <hi>It hath been the deſign of the</hi> Turk, <hi>ever ſince the Conqueſt of</hi> Rhodes <hi>and</hi> Cyprus, <hi>to gain the</hi> Kingdom of Candia; <hi>and that for this reaſon, becauſe then the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>being deſtitute of all Harbours in the</hi> Eaſt, <hi>he might with the greater ſecurity fall upon them in the</hi> Weſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1645 (when all Chriſtendom was at variance) <hi>Ibraim</hi> the Father of the now <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Monarch,</hi> in the depth of a long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued peace, when leaſt expected, began this War by ſetting upon the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and gave this out as the pretended cauſe of this Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel.</p>
            <p>In the former <hi>Agreement</hi> ratified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded between them, it ſeems, among many other <hi>Articles</hi> that the <hi>Republick</hi> had tyed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58480:8"/>themſelves up to perform, this was one, they did engage to deny the <hi>Knights of Malta</hi> ſhelter in any of their <hi>Ports</hi> or <hi>Harbours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1644, it fell out that the Gallies of that Order ſeiz'd a <hi>Sultana,</hi> and took her, who with three Millions of Crowns deſign'd a Pilgrimage to <hi>Mecha.</hi> They ſteering homewards laden with this rich booty, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd by the unſeaſonableneſs of the Weather, or for want of freſh water, clancularly, and by ſtealth, to ſtrike into a by-Port of <hi>Candia,</hi> whence after ſome refreſhment they return'd ſafely to their own <hi>Iſle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next year the <hi>Turk</hi> furniſheth out a Fleet of 460 Sail great and ſmall, ſolemnly proteſting to the <hi>Senates Ambaſſadors,</hi> that theſe preparations were for the <hi>Iſle of Malta;</hi> but when they had paſt by them, and ſteer'd a courſe almoſt as far as <hi>Sapienza,</hi> they ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly tackt about, and landed ſixty thouſand men, who immediately ſate down before <hi>Canea</hi> without the leaſt declaration of War. The <hi>Venetian</hi> being thus ſo unexpectedly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd, made all poſſible proviſion to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a defenſive poſture; but before they could rouze their ancient and accuſtom'd courage, they loſt the whole <hi>Kingdom,</hi> except <hi>Candia,</hi> and <hi>Carabuſa, Spina longa</hi> and <hi>Suda,</hi> three adjoyning Inſulets. The <hi>Grand Signior</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:58480:9"/>being elated and puft up with this ſucceſs, gain'd by that happy crime (in his opinion) proſperous treachery, own'd the War o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly, and publickly declar'd the <hi>Senates</hi> ſheltring of the <hi>Malteſes</hi> to be the cauſe; though 'twas privately decreed, that if they met with any conſiderable force or reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the firſt aſſault, that the <hi>Captain Baſſa</hi> ſhould loſe his head (to pacifie the <hi>Senate</hi>) for attempting it without Order, and ſo to perſwade them it was onely a <hi>Capricio</hi> of his own brain, and a plot of his own contrivance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1648, they ſoon were Maſters of the Field, and began the <hi>Siege</hi> of <hi>Candia</hi> with ſo furious an onſet, that they made a breach and entred it, and for the ſpace of ſeven hours vvere vvithin the <hi>Town;</hi> but the <hi>Defendants</hi> by their valour beat them out with infinite loſs and damage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1649, they made a ſecond attempt, which proving fruitleſs and ineffectual, they then left it, never expecting to win it by ſtorm. On a riſing ground about three Miles from the old, they have built another Town, called <hi>New Candia,</hi> which is the Reſidence of the <hi>Turkiſh Baſſa,</hi> where they have ſtrongly fortified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, blocking up the <hi>City;</hi> ſo that now there is no commerce at all but by Sea, which fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the <hi>Candiots</hi> with plenty of proviſions, and all other neceſſaries whatſoever.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:58480:9"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT Of the Siege of CANDIA.</head>
            <p>HAving given you a Deſcription of <hi>Candia,</hi> we will proceed to the laſt Siege and Surrender thereof, which we have, no account of till about <hi>September</hi> 1666; and then all hopes of peace being laid aſide, the <hi>Turks</hi> made ſome attempts upon <hi>Almiſſa,</hi> a ſtrong place in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> but with little or no ſucceſs; and much about the ſame time fell upon <hi>Marcaſca,</hi> a Town upon the Sea-coaſts, which they intended to attaque; but <hi>General Cornaro</hi> rallied up thoſe Forces he had, and could get together ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and marched towards the <hi>Enemy,</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out ſeveral Barques and Gallies, that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58480:10"/>might play on them with their Cannon, and do execution: yet before he appear'd, the <hi>Turks</hi> had made an aſſault, but were ſo warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, receiv'd, that they were, beat off with the loſs of nigh 150 of their men which were left dead upon the place, beſides a conſiderable number of wounded perſons which they brought off with them: and a few days after, made another aſſault upon the <hi>Town;</hi> but <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Cornaro</hi> drew out of the <hi>Garriſon</hi> all the men privately in the night, undermining the <hi>Fort,</hi> with an intent to blow up the <hi>Turks:</hi> they came up furiouſly to the Walls, but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no <hi>Enemy</hi> grew jealous of the <hi>Stratagem</hi> and retreated, and in a ſhort time ſaw the <hi>Mine</hi> fired, which made them march farther into the Country; but the <hi>Venetian Forces</hi> returned to <hi>Spalatto,</hi> and there continued to obſerve the <hi>Enemies</hi> motion</p>
            <p>Little was done by them till towards the latter end of this inſtant <hi>September,</hi> at which time ſome <hi>Turks</hi> were diſcovered before <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Nuova;</hi> but they onely fired a few Guns and returned back to their Quarters; the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon being well fortified, and furniſhed with men and proviſions. At the ſame time they made an attempt upon <hi>Gradan,</hi> a ſtrong Fort near <hi>Marcaſca;</hi> but they were ſo vigorouſly entertained by the Beſieged, that they were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58480:10"/>forced to quit their Poſts with the loſs of four hundred men.</p>
            <p>In <hi>October</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> of <hi>Canea</hi> took the Field vvith their peeces of Cannon, intending to leavy Contributions in the Country; and to prevent all information, ſet ſtrong Guards up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the adjoyning Sea-coaſts.</p>
            <p>Tovvards the latter end of this Month <hi>Signior Barbaro, Proveditor-General,</hi> arrived in <hi>Candia;</hi> his Predeceſſor <hi>Signior Priuli</hi> being upon his departure to <hi>Dalmatia</hi> in the quality of General.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Morlacks</hi> (vvho are <hi>Croats</hi> or <hi>Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> ſo called from the Hills where they formerly lived, being a ſort of people that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the Turkiſh bondage, and put themſelves under the Senates Government) about this time made ſeveral incurſions into the Turkiſh Quarters vvith great ſucceſs, taking a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable number of Slaves, and bringing ſeveral droves of Cattle along vvith them.</p>
            <p>In <hi>November</hi> the Grand Signior declar'd his reſolution to make War with the Republique, by making preparations both by Sea and Land to attempt <hi>Candia</hi> the next Spring; to vvhich purpoſe he lays great Subſidies upon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple throughout all his Dominions, and by his light Gallies hath landed ſome Forces in <hi>Canea.</hi> This month alſo the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58480:11"/>arrived in <hi>Canea,</hi> and was received with great joy, which the <hi>Turks</hi> manifeſted by many days feaſting; who reſolved to take the Field as ſoon as the Seaſon would permit, and to lay cloſe Siege to <hi>Candia:</hi> The <hi>Grand Signior</hi> himſelf giving all poſſible incouragement to the Levies, and promiſing extraordinary pay to thoſe that will liſt themſelves among the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> with an exemption from all Taxes and Subſidies. The <hi>Turks</hi> preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being now very conſiderable for ſome weighty deſigne, the <hi>Senate</hi> doth ſtrengthen the City again it all attempts; and though it be ſo well fortified by Nature, yet they defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with above 1700 pieces of Cannon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well furniſht with expert Veteran Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Souldiers.</p>
            <p>In <hi>December</hi> the <hi>Grand Viſiers</hi> intentions to beſiege <hi>Candia</hi> are daily more and more diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, which occaſion'd General <hi>Cornaro</hi> and Marquiſs <hi>Villa</hi> to go to <hi>Candia</hi> with a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of choice men to its aſſiſtance. Towards the latter end of this Month the <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> lay about <hi>Retimo,</hi> having a Body of 40000 <hi>Turks</hi> drawn together in the Field; and the Marquiſs <hi>Villa</hi> diſpoſed all things in good order, and raiſed ſeveral outworks which did very much contribute to the ſtrengthing of the City. About this time there was talk
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58480:11"/>of a Treaty, to make the Chriſtians careleſs in their defence.</p>
            <p>In <hi>January</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> drew near <hi>Candia,</hi> and the Garriſon made ſeveral brisk Sallies with ſome loſs to the <hi>Turks,</hi> in one of which <hi>Vertmiller</hi> was ſlightly hurt. The <hi>Grand Viſier</hi> upon a general Muſter of his Forces in the Iſle of <hi>Candia,</hi> found his Army conſiſted of 23000 men, and iſſued out Orders to all parts ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning in the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominions, to haſten re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruits of Men and Ammunition, in order to the ſpeedy beſieging of <hi>Candia,</hi> and to caſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral vaſt Guns of extraordinary buſineſs, to be employed in that ſervice. The Chief <hi>Viſier</hi> continued ſtill at <hi>Retimo,</hi> making all neceſſary proviſions for his intended deſign; and ſent ſeveral of his Officers to take a view of the City and her Fortifications, which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs did take daily care to ſtrengthen, and for the removal of all combuſtible matter out of the Houſes, to avoid the execution of their Morter-pieces. Toward the latter end of this Month, the <hi>Venetian</hi> Convoy arrived at <hi>Candia,</hi> under the command of <hi>Semitecolo;</hi> and twelve Gallies laden with <hi>Bisket</hi> were ſent into <hi>Candia</hi> by the Admiral of their Fleet riding at <hi>Paros,</hi> whoſe Squadrons were conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually cruiſing about the Sea to intercept the Proviſions deſign'd for the <hi>Turks.</hi> The Grand
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58480:12"/>Viſier was now indiſpos'd at <hi>Retimo,</hi> but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the ſtrengthning of <hi>New Candia,</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to raiſe a Battery near the <hi>Lazaretto,</hi> to hinder the paſſage of the Republique's Veſſels for the relief of the City; againſt which the <hi>Venetian</hi> Forces caſt up a ſtrong Fort to beat them off, and prevent their nearer approaches. The <hi>Sultan</hi> then ſent freſh commands to the <hi>Viſier,</hi> to imploy the utmoſt of his power and endeavours for the gaining of the Metropolis. The <hi>Viſier</hi> being diſſatisfied with the former proceedings of the <hi>Baſſa</hi>'s of <hi>Canea</hi> and <hi>Candia Nuova,</hi> he beheaded them both, and uſed the like ſerverity to ſeveral Officers, under pretence that they were wanting in the performance of their Duties the laſt Summer. He hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways along with him the <hi>Aga</hi> of the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> as Pay-maſter to the Army, whoſe advice ſways extreamly with him in all matters of Importance. In the interim the <hi>Senate</hi> is ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to defend their Territories againſt the common Enemy. Now the Treaty that was ſet on foot by the Prime <hi>Viſier</hi> is wholly bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, being reſolv'd to proſecute the Siege vigorouſly. The <hi>Viſier</hi> about the latter of <hi>January,</hi> or the beginning of <hi>February,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Retimo</hi> to <hi>Candia Nuova,</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to go back to <hi>Canea.</hi> The <hi>Turks</hi> laboured hard at the Batteries before <hi>Candia,</hi> and chiefly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58480:12"/>that near <hi>Lazaretto,</hi> but with little ſucceſs; for the beſieged plyed them very cloſely from their new Fort, and made a Sally, forcing the <hi>Turks</hi> from their Batteries, killing five hundred upon the place, and taking forty ſix Priſoners, with the loſs of forty men onely. The Prime <hi>Viſier</hi> now return'd to <hi>Canea,</hi> as 'twas thought to continue there, as a place of ſecurity during the Infection, the Plague raging ſo violently in the Camp; and their Admiral <hi>Baſſa</hi> to the <hi>Dardanellos</hi> with the major part of the Fleet.</p>
            <p>In <hi>February</hi> the Grand <hi>Viſier</hi> in perſon with a party of <hi>Turks</hi> took a view of the Poſts, the better to form his Leaguer againſt the City; but he was ſo warmly entertained with Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, Morter-pieces, and Granadoes, that they fell into ſome diſorder; which the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perceiving, made a ſmart Sally upon him, forcing him to quit the place and flee to <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Nuova,</hi> leaving his Nephew ſlain by a Cannon-ſhot from the Walls dead upon the place, with other conſiderable perſons. At <hi>Canea</hi> he remain'd in expectation of his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors of twenty thouſand men from the Grand <hi>Signior:</hi> and in the mean time the Garriſon threw down all the Works caſt up by the <hi>Turks</hi> againſt the Town, and levelled all their Trenches.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58480:13"/>
            <p>The Turkiſh Army was now very much viſited with the Plague, and deſtitute of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, ſo that the <hi>Viſier</hi> diſperſed his Forces about the Iſland. And much about this time, Signior <hi>Nicola Lyon,</hi> Commander of one of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ships, met with a Turkiſh Veſſel laden with Proviſions, under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of ſix Gallies, who after an hours diſpute took her; at which the <hi>Viſier</hi> was ſo highly incenſed, that he took off the heads of ſix of the Captains, as being too remiſs, and want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duty and courage to defend her. Towards the latter end of this Month, the <hi>Turks</hi> with a conſiderable party Marched hear <hi>Candia,</hi> but were repulſed with no inconſiderable loſs; in which encounter two Renegadoes of note were taken priſoners, and carried into <hi>Candia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> Signior <hi>Pada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino,</hi> the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ambaſſador, arriv'd at <hi>Canea;</hi> upon whoſe approach, the Turkiſh Forces by order from the Grand Viſier, being about 40000 in number, were drawn together in his view: alſo a Body of <hi>Turks</hi> a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came up to the Walls of <hi>Candia</hi> in a bravado, but were receiv'd ſo ſtoutly by a party that Sallied out againſt them, that they were forced to quit their ſtation in confuſion and great diſorder. In this Month, about the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58480:13"/>middle thereof, a Turkiſh Gallie carried off by the Chriſtian Slaves aboard of her, was brought into the Fleet: the manner of the ſurpriſe was as followeth: There were 180 <hi>Turks</hi> and upwards aboard this Gally, with their Officers, among whom there hapned to be a Renegado <hi>Grecian,</hi> who proving a penitent Apoſtate, contriv'd this plot, to free himſelf and the Chriſtian Slaves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to the Oars: He went down pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately into the Hold, and made ſeveral holes to let in the water; and having ſo done, came haſtily upon the Deck, crying out that the Veſſel had ſprung ſo many and ſo great Leaks, that it was irrecoverably loſt: hereupon the <hi>Turks</hi> made immediately to a Rock not far off them, where they ran aſhore: the Slaves laying hold of this opportunity, row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off the Gally, ſtopped the Leaks, brought her to <hi>Paros,</hi> and preſented her to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-General; who preſently ſent two Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies well arm'd and man'd to the Rock, where they took all the <hi>Turks</hi> (who were old Souldiers and perſons of Eminency) five or ſix onely excepted, who were drown'd, endeavouring to ſave themſelves by ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p>In <hi>March,</hi> ſome of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ships ſucceſsfully engaged with the Caravan or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58480:14"/>Convoy from <hi>Alexandria;</hi> the Admiral whereof had 300 ſtout Souldiers aboard of him brought out of <hi>Barbary;</hi> the Veſſel belonging to <hi>Tunis,</hi> which was commanded by the <hi>Sanſack</hi> of <hi>Grand Cayro,</hi> or Viceroy of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who was by Orders from the Grand Signior to go to the aſſiſtance of the Grand Viſier, and to take upon him the command of the Baſſa of <hi>Canea:</hi> he brought with him 2000 Souldiers raiſed upon his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to that purpoſe, with ſeveral Officers, who had made a ſolemn vow to the Grand Signior to do their utmoſt in the War, and to loſe their lives rather then to quit the Siege. This Veſſel during the diſpute took fire, and was conſum'd with its fraught, to the value of 200000 Reals, and 50000 Zecchins deſigned to pay the Grand Viſiers Army, beſides the private Gold of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers. Many of the men ſeeking their ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Boat, were taken and made ſlaves; and ſeveral other Veſſels of that Convoy fell into the Chriſtians hands with a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Booty, and one among the reſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with noble Horſes for ſervice was taken by a Chriſtian Privateer that commanded a Pink. The Viſier hearing of this ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, cut off the heads of three Captains that arriv'd at <hi>Canea,</hi> and commanded ten
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58480:14"/>freſh Gallies to reſcue the reſt of the Convoy, and conduct them ſafe to <hi>Canea,</hi> upon pain of death.</p>
            <p>About this time there was a Truce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them for a ſeaſon, for the repair of the Ruines on both ſides occaſion'd by a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Earthquake that hapned on <hi>Holy-Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and ſeveral others ſince: in the former, a great part of <hi>Albania</hi> ſuffer'd; it threw down many Houſes in <hi>Cattaro,</hi> with a great part of the Wall towards the Sea, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 600 perſons at leaſt; and <hi>Buda</hi> was wholly ſwallowed up, in which there pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed the like number of people, both theſe places being ſubject to the Republique; and <hi>Dulcigno</hi> and <hi>Caſtel Nuova,</hi> two places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Turks,</hi> were both ſunk; which was the cauſe of this Truce between the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> and the <hi>Turk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>General <hi>Cornaro</hi> and the Marquiſs <hi>Degl' Oddi</hi> were imyloyed to repair the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages ſuffered at <hi>Cattaro</hi> by this Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</p>
            <p>In the Month of <hi>April</hi> 1667, the Grand Viſier plained the Country for five Miles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether about the Port of <hi>Suda;</hi> cutting down the Trees and Vines, and driving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the Cattle, that the Garriſon might not be ſupplyed from thoſe parts: whilſt in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58480:15"/>the mean time the people belonging to the Republique were very induſtrious, and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſeveral Out-works which did very much ſtrengthen <hi>Candia;</hi> beſides, Captain-General <hi>Moroſini</hi> ſent large Supplies of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and Moneys into the City in ſeveral Veſſels commanded by Captain <hi>Gio. Moroſini.</hi> But the Viſier finding his Army to conſiſt of 50000 men, having received ſupplies from the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Court, raiſed his Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries againſt the Fort of St. <hi>Demetrius;</hi> who was manfully withſtood by the Defendants, with ſome loſs to the Beſiegers. The <hi>Turks</hi> having found an opportunity to convoy forty Gallies with Souldiers and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into <hi>Canea,</hi> were ſo much incouraged hereby, that they a little after gave a buſie aſſault to <hi>Suda,</hi> a conſiderable Fortreſs of the <hi>Venetians;</hi> but were beaten off with much ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>In <hi>May,</hi> the Turkiſh Saiques taking their way by the South-Sea, arrived at <hi>Gira Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> and put aſhore 5000 <hi>Janiſaries;</hi> which ſo heartned the Army, that the Viſier reſolved upon the Siege of <hi>Candia:</hi> to this end he diſarm'd all the Gallies, imploying the Souldies in his Army, and the Slaves as Pioneers to work in the Trenches; and ſpeedily raiſed three Batteries againſt the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58480:15"/>three principal Bulwarks of that City; which the Chriſtians defended with extraordinary valour. But the Viſier being ſenſible of the Grand Signior's high diſpleaſure, attempted them with all his force, and played upon their Forts with his Batteries, intrenching 5000 men before the Fort St. <hi>Demetrius,</hi> battering it with 100 of pieces of Cannon; he being then in expectation of the recruit of 8000 men from <hi>Morea:</hi> And the Baſſa of <hi>Boſſina</hi> preſſed one man out of every Houſe in all the Countries about him; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting <hi>Licia</hi> and <hi>Corbaccia,</hi> who denyed it, pretending their inability to go to War, by reaſon of a Famine lately among them. The <hi>Turks</hi> had now laid a cloſe Siege to <hi>Candia,</hi> battering it in four places; but the Viſier firſt demoliſhed the Town of <hi>New Candia</hi> (formerly built by the <hi>Turks</hi>) becauſe that the materials thereof might be uſeful in raiſing their Works, and to prevent his Souldiers retreating thither. The Ports againſt which he made his Batteries, were <hi>Bethlem, Sabionera, Jeſus</hi> and St. <hi>Demetrius;</hi> the men imployed againſt them were 40000 in number, beſides 12000 Pioneers. But the Chriſtians were much incouraged by the arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of the Convoy under the command of <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiniano,</hi> Commiſſary of the Proviſions, who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58480:16"/>had ſent 70000 Ducats into the Town, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all other neceſſaries, and brought with him 75000 more, which vvere conveyed to the Captain-General for the uſe of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata. The Siege vvas very induſtriouſly managed by the Grand Viſier, their Forces vvell ordered, and their Cannons continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally roaring; they gave a ſtout aſſault, but vvere repulſt with conſiderable damage. The Viſier being oblig'd upon his ovvn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to hazard his vvhole Army, made ſix furious aſſaults upon the City, but vvas in all beaten off vvith the loſs of 12000 men, at leaſt, in theſe attempts. For tvven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days time that the <hi>Turks</hi> had ſpent in the Siege of <hi>Candia,</hi> they gained not ſo much as one foot of ground; and their great Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and Cannon did little injury, being at too great a diſtance, and mounted too high, ſo that by falling upon the higheſt Houſes they onely beat off ſome Tiles, and threvv dovvn ſome Chimnies; vvhich vvas all the execution that vvas done. The Chriſtian Privateers did do the Republique excellent Service at Sea; among others one called the <hi>Notali,</hi> having ſeven hundred men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, took in fevv days above tvventy prizes.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Villa</hi> made a luſty Sally out of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58480:16"/>
               <hi>Candia</hi> vvith 2000 choice men, vvho fell upon one of the <hi>Turks</hi> Poſts vvith ſuch courage and reſolution, that he made a great ſlaughter among them, they being out of order; but at length rallying together, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued the General, vvho drevv them into a place prepar'd for that purpoſe, and then ordered the Mines to be fired; vvhich vvas ſo ſucceſsfully effected, that according to the information of a Renegado afterwards, near 3000 <hi>Turks</hi> were deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>On the 28 of <hi>May,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> began ſome violent attaques upon the Fort near <hi>Bethlem,</hi> and the Gate <hi>Panigra;</hi> and that morning they played upon the Bulwarks with two pieces of Cannon, which were anſwer'd by the Guns from their Counter-batteries and Courtines.</p>
            <p>The 29 the Enemy made nearer approaches, and began with two Guns onely to batter the Bulwarks of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> but the Chriſtians with their Guns from the Gallies, and thoſe from the Works, play'd upon the <hi>Turks</hi> ſo warmly, that they were diſordered, and the Grand Viſier forced to change his Poſt.</p>
            <p>On the 30 the <hi>Turks</hi> onely wrought hard to raiſe a Battery againſt St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Fort.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58480:17"/>
            <p>The 31 the Enemy aſſaulted the Fort with great fury; and in that days ſervice Captain <hi>Galeazzo,</hi> an Officer of <hi>Piedmont,</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately ſlain by a Shot in the Out-work of St. <hi>Maries,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Caſtaneuf;</hi> but the <hi>Savoyards</hi> under his command, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his death, did fall that night upon the <hi>Turks</hi> with Hand-Granadoes, Swords and Piſtols, aſſiſted by ſome other Forces, and made a great confuſion among them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling them to leave their Works with much diſorder. The <hi>Savoyards</hi> followed them into one of their Redoubts, and ſlew a conſiderable number of them; the Guns from the Town in the mean time play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Enemy, to hinder their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the firſt, there was little or no action; onely the Enemies Cannon firing, diſmounted a Gun in the Fort <hi>Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nengo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the ſecond, they formed another Battery, and fired at the Beſieged with two other pieces of Cannon, bringing up a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liot with another Veſſel to furniſh them with Proviſions, wherewith they were la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſent out two Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to ingage them, but they were ſo ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defended by their Batteries, that the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58480:17"/>Gallies were forced to betake themſelves to their own Fort for protection.</p>
            <p>The ſame morning, the <hi>Turks</hi> laid an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh near the Out-work of <hi>Mocenigo,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercept the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and prevent the relief of their Guards; but they were valiantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted and put to flight, leaving many of them dead upon the place, beſides thoſe that were kill'd in the retreat, which were more in number.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the third, the <hi>Turks</hi> ſpent this morning in interring their dead, and in Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral-Ceremonies; but that afternoon they fired very thick upon the Town, with Bullets of 80, 90, and 120 pound weight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the fourth, they approached within a ſtones caſt of the Walls; and that night there was a reſolute skirmiſh before <hi>Panigra,</hi> where they were receiv'd with Volleys of Musket, and plenty of Cannon-ſhot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the fifth, in the morning, near the Works of St. <hi>Mary</hi> they raiſed a new Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, playing upon the Beſieged with four great Guns; and wrought very hard to caſt up a Trench to ſecure a Paſſage for their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, in which they were defended by a great number of Muſqueteers, drawn thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for that deſigne; but they had ſuch a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58480:18"/>peal of Ordnance, Small-ſhot and Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does from the Town, that they deſiſted from their enterprize, with an extraordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary loſs of men; the Beſieged onely had ſome few Souldiers wounded, but loſt not one man that day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the ſixth, the Guns onely played on both ſides.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh, the <hi>Turks</hi> plyed again their Works, and made their approaches with greater preparation then formerly, working under ground.</p>
            <p>The eighth inſtant they raiſed another Battery againſt St. <hi>Andrews</hi> Bulwark, and endeavoured the reparation of their old Battery at the <hi>Lazaretto;</hi> but the Marquiſs <hi>Villa</hi> ordered a Counter-battery well plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Guns to be made to ſecure the place, and in his retreat by the <hi>Mole,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſlight hurt in his hand by the flying of the Stones, occaſion'd from Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non-ſhort that ſtrook upon the Walls. That night they made a Sally from the Half-moon of <hi>Mocenigo;</hi> where there was a ſharp fight which continued for many hours, but concluded with great ſlaughter of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by the Cannon and Morter-pieccs from the City-works.</p>
            <p>On the nineteenth of <hi>July</hi> Signior <hi>Baroni</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58480:18"/>with two Gallies, and not long after Signior <hi>Carenzo Piſani,</hi> who was choſen Proveditor for <hi>Candia,</hi> entred the Port with Succours for the City: and the ſame Evening his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency Captain-General <hi>Moroſini</hi> followed them <hi>Incognito</hi> with two Gallies more. He was at his landing near the <hi>Arſenal,</hi> received by Signior <hi>Barbaro</hi> with great joy, and all the Martial Ceremonies uſual upon ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; who preſented him with the Keys of the City; and with a great Train of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Souldiers, accompanied with Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>Maro</hi> Proveditor to the Fleet; and the Proveditor of the Iſle attended him to his Coach, and the Lodgings prepar'd for him: He paſſed under a Triumphal Arch erected in the great Street for him, being met alſo by the Cavalry at the Gates of the City, and ſaluted by the great Guns; the whole City teſtifying their extraordinary joy and ſatisfaction for his arrival, by their loud Acclamations and rare Fire-works.</p>
            <p>The next morning the <hi>Turks</hi> at break of day diſcharged a great Volley of Muſquets and Cannon againſt the City, which the Beſieged ſcorning to be indebted to them) return'd from the Walls.</p>
            <p>The ſame morning Colonel <hi>Chateauneuf</hi> attaqued a Redoubt caſt up by the Enemy
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58480:19"/>near <hi>Panigra,</hi> to give the Captain-General ſome ſignal teſtimony of the courage and reſolution of the Beſieged, and very freely threw his Hand-granadoes among them: but the <hi>Turks</hi> being prepar'd for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, iſſued out, and preſſed very hard and cloſe upon them; yet they, being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by another party commanded by the Captains <hi>Caſtelli, Bonefort,</hi> and a third whoſe name we have no certain knovvledge of, renewed their aſſault, and did conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable execution upon the <hi>Turks:</hi> but the Alarm being by this time grown warm, and great numbers coming to their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, the <hi>Candiots</hi> retir'd to the Covert way of, the Fort <hi>Panigra,</hi> and the Enemy purſued them with great ſhouting; and notwithſtanding the Paliſadoes, and a Guard of forty Muſqueteers that play'd upon them with their Vollies, they were forc'd to leave their Colonel <hi>Chateauneuf</hi> behind them, and ſhelter themſelves in the Moat; but he with an inconſiderable number of Officers valiantly beat off the Enemy twice or thrice together, and was at laſt relieved by Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major <hi>Motta,</hi> who Sallying out of the Fort, beat back the <hi>Turks</hi> into their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt with a great ſlaughter; he himſelf receiving a ſhot in the breaſt, but without
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58480:19"/>hurt, his Armor being well tryed, and of proof. In this attaque the Chriſtians came off with the loſs of one Serjeant, two Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and two others wounded.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time Colonel <hi>Martinom,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of <hi>Panigra,</hi> ſent out twelve Souldiers with Granadoes, and forty Foot-men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Major <hi>Bricheras</hi> Lieutenant, to aſſault another Redoubt caſt up on the right hand of the Fort; which they performed with great courage, beating out the <hi>Turks,</hi> and putting many of them to the Sword: but the Enemy growing more numerous, they retreated, their Lieutenant being ſhot dead under the Redoubt, but like true Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, reſolving not to leave the Body of their Officer in the power of the Enemy, they return'd upon them, and with great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor forced them to give ground, taking up the Body, and retiring to their Works with much glory and renown.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Savoyards</hi> alſo, being but 60 Officers and Souldiers, with Granadoes, under the Command of Colonel <hi>Torre,</hi> Sallied out from the <hi>Ravelin</hi> of <hi>Bethlem,</hi> and fell upon the Enemies Line, where a Body of <hi>Turks</hi> ſtood upon their Guard to defend the Pioneers; and there hapned a very hot diſpute; but they ſending out a recruit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58480:20"/>of <hi>Savoyards</hi> ſo aſſiſt them, the Enemy was beaten from the Line, and forced to ſeek their ſafety in ſome of their Redoubts, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving 60 of their party dead upon the place, four of whoſe heads the <hi>Candiots</hi> brought with them, and preſented to the Captain-General, whoſe valour in this noble attempt was rewarded with forty Reals; and in this Service they were ſo fortunate, as to come off with the loſs of a ſingle Souldier. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Arborio</hi> and <hi>Marino,</hi> with the Count <hi>Bruſano</hi> Captain of the Guard to Marquiſs <hi>Villa,</hi> ſallied out of the Poſt of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> with a party of fifty men; forced the <hi>Turks</hi> out of two ſeveral Redoubts, kill'd a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number of them, and loſt onely one Serjeant.</p>
            <p>There was alſo great execution done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Enemy by a Squadron that iſſued from the Fort of St. <hi>Demetrius,</hi> who ſlaughtred many of them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> being by this time ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of their ſucceſsleſs procedings by Batteries and open force, were wholly bent upon their Mines, imploying conſtantly night and day ten thouſand Pioneers to work in them; whereupon they advanced greatly in their approaches, the drineſs of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon contributing very much to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58480:20"/>and laboured extreamly to meet with the Mines from the Out-works; ſome whereof the Chriſtians did ſpring and blow up, which proved very fatal and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the <hi>Turks.</hi> In the interim the great ſhot fly very liberally on both ſides, but with little damage to the City, onely beating down the tops of ſome Churches and high Houſes, with the loſs of four or five per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The <hi>Turks</hi> ſtill plyed the City very cloſe with their Guns from the Batteries; and throwing Morter-pieces into the Town, with little loſs to the Beſieged, but great loſs to the Beſiegers. The Chriſtian Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayres did very conſiderable ſervice by crui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the Sea, and in the <hi>Archipelago;</hi> by which means they did infinitely inrich themſelves, having taken ſeveral great Prizes, and intercepted the Enemies Veſſels which were laden with Proviſions intended for their Armies ſupply.</p>
            <p>Now the Turks began to be very ſparing of their Cannon-ſhot, which was ſuppoſed to be for want of Powder; who finding little or no ſucceſs thereby, they fell to their Mines, and ſprung one made under the Out-work of the <hi>Half-moon</hi> of <hi>Mocenigo,</hi> and entred the breach, took poſſeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; killing fifty Souldiers placed there to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58480:21"/>defend it: The Enemy being elevated with this ſucceſs, ſent 3000 men to make good the place, of which they continued Maſters for the ſpace of one day and a half; but Marquiſs <hi>Villa</hi> knowing that it might prove advantagious to them in attaquing the next Work, was reſolved to diſpoſſeſs them; and therefore he nobly iſſued out with a Party of able Souldiers, and at the ſame time gave fire to a Mine, formerly made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, though undiſcovered by the Enemy, which blew up ſo ſucceſsfully, that the Turks perſiht moſt miſerably in the ruines; and then the Marqueſs falling in among the reſt, after a ſharp and bloody fight of ſix hours continuance, beat them off, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain'd the place, with the loſs of 300 of his own men, and above 2000 Turks.</p>
            <p>The next day the Grand Viſier, having had ſo great a loſs of his beſt Souldiers, called a Council of his principal Baſſa's; where it was reſolv'd, that they ſhould ſend a Trumpeter to the Captain-General, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that Signor <hi>Giaverina</hi> might come and treat with them in order to an agreement: but Colonel <hi>Vecchia</hi> went out in his ſtead, they not approving of ſending out the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer at preſent; and he was courteouſly receiv'd by the whole Army, but eſpecially
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58480:21"/>by the Viſier, who treated him with a coſtly Collation; telling him, That if his General wanted Proviſions, he would freely ſend him what his Camp did afford: but the Colonel after thanks return'd for his civil proffer, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him that the City was ſo plentifully ſupplyed by the Fleet, that they could not ſtand in need of any thing: he was ſafely ſent back to the City, with much importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that <hi>Giaverina</hi> might be admitted to treat with them; which vvas at laſt conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended unto, and he vvas receiv'd by the Turks with great joy, vvho vvelcom'd him vvith all their Cannons, and ſaluted him vvith ſeveral Muſqueteers; the general cry through the vvhole Camp being nothing but <hi>Peace, Peace.</hi> At this time the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> receiv'd very certain intelligence, that the Turks Army did not conſiſt of above 25000 men, the Svvord and Sickneſs having ſvvept avvay the one half of their Army; though ſuccours vvere daily expected from <hi>Morea.</hi> About this time the Captain Baſſa vvas diſcovered near the Iſle <hi>Cerigo,</hi> vvhere he had landed ſeveral of his men, but the <hi>Venetian</hi> Gallies coming to ingage him, he put off to Sea with ſuch haſte, that he left 200 of his men behind him, vvhich vvere taken by the <hi>Candiots</hi> and made ſlaves.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:58480:22"/>
            <p>But this Treaty like the reſt ſoon vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and came to nothing. The Turks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing ſtill their Works under-ground, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all their confidence in the Mines, vvhich the Beſieged laboured to fruſtrate by their Counter-Mines; yet they applyed their greateſt force and Works againſt <hi>Panigra;</hi> labouring hard at their Mines, vvhich they often ſprung on every ſide, and in the mean time plyed the Tovvn and Fort, eſpecially, vvith great and ſmall ſhot: but the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged are not backvvard, either in the one or the other, ſo that the Enemies deſigns prove unſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>Before <hi>Panigra</hi> the Turks raiſed one very large Battery that had nine great Guns, from vvhence they played furiouſly for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days together, and vvere anſvvered by the Beſieged, vvith extraordinary loſs to the Beſiegers; for above 12000 Turks periſhed by the <hi>Candiots</hi> Sallies, Shot, Granadoes and Mines, with ſeveral Captains of Note, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced Officers among them. The Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans having loſt ſince the beginning of the Siege about 1000 men, with ſome Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; among whom <hi>Baron Baroni</hi> is one, vvho vvas kill'd by a Muſquet-ſhot on the 26 of <hi>July.</hi> And the Ladies, &amp; others of that tender Sex, did give as ſignal teſtimonies of their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58480:22"/>courage &amp; valour in the defence of the Town, as the men; among vvhom the Wife of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Motta,</hi> vvho vvas Coloneſs of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Women, behaved her ſelf vvith incredible reſolution and infinite courage; vvhoſe death vvas much lamented, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unhappily kill'd by the fall of a Wall, beaten dovvn by the Beſiegers Cannon; vvho ſtill are very intent upon the Siege, and approach nearer and nearer the Tovvn, by the daily ſpringing of their Mines, ſhaking the vvhole City vvith the force of them; and are conſtantly aſſaulting, but as conſtantly repuls'd and beaten off; and 300 of them loſt their lives, beſides a great many more buried in their ovvn mines, by the blovving up of one of the Venetians Counter-mines. But the Turks by their frequently repeated and continued Batteries, had by this time made a great breach in the left Horn of the Fort <hi>Panigra,</hi> and another in that of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenigno;</hi> and on the eleventh of <hi>Anguſt</hi> they gave a violent aſſault to both; and to divert the <hi>Candiots,</hi> did at the ſame time ſtorm the Tovvn at ſeveral other places; but by the courage of the Beſieged vvere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very vvhere repuls'd vvith great ſlaughter; the Beſiegers leaving many of their dead behind them, vvhoſe heads adorn the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58480:23"/>Houſes of the Venetian Officers, vvherevvith they are ſet round, as Trophies of their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and revvards of their reſolution. Yet the Turks are no vvays diſcouraged, but are principally incouraged by a Renegado Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit called <hi>La Grange,</hi> who is courteouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd by the Viſier, and wholly ſway'd by his advice.</p>
            <p>The Turks now make uſe of ſeveral Gunners that are Chriſtians, whom they have compell'd into their ſervice by force, or drawn them in by flattery; and to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the reſt, they cut off the head of one of them, who was ſuſpected not to have fired his Gun to the beſt advange. They ſtill continued ſpringing of their Mines; which occaſions many daily ſharp encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and the courage of the <hi>Candiots</hi> is as frequently ſignaliz'd by the great ſlaughter of the Turks: which ſo incenſed the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, that he commanded a general aſſault, which was perform'd with a noiſe as great as their fury, and for a conſiderable time continued with much obſtinacy; but they finding the greateſt loſs to be their own, and the Defendants inconſiderable; the Viſier gave over the aſſault, whoſe trouble and almoſt deſpair is encreaſed by the great wants of neceſſary Proviſions in the Camp,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58480:23"/>and the difficulty of being ſupplyed, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the indefatigable induſtry &amp; diligence of the Venetian Squadrons, who ſo continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. cruiſe before <hi>Canea,</hi> that they cannot ſteal in with their Veſſels: inſomuch that the Turks grew full of deſpondencie, conſidering that in ſo long a Siege, after ſo many men loſt, ſo many aſſaults made, and ſo many Mines ſprung, they had not as yet made themſelves maſters of any one Out-work of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and though the Turks were in great wants, yet the Venetians were deſtitute of nothing that was neceſſary, either of men, money, Ammunition, or any other Proviſions whatſoever.</p>
            <p>But the Turks ſtill made daily aſſaults, ſpringing freſh Mines; yet by the prudence and conduct of the Beſieged, their attempts have been fruſtrated. Now the Turks Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non had torne ſome houſes, and beat down ſome part of their Walls; but the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Granadoes ſhot from the Enemies Morter-pieces, did the greateſt prejudice to the Town.</p>
            <p>Now the Captain-general, for prevention of all ſurprizes, commanded all his Souldiers to keep their Poſts allotted them, by a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrict Proclamation; and Ordered that all ſorts of Victuals ſhould be ſold near the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:58480:24"/>Walls of the Town, to remove all pretences for their abſence.</p>
            <p>Then the Turks raiſed a Battery near the Poſt, but to no purpoſe; and bent the moſt conſiderable force they had againſt the Out-works of <hi>Mocenigo</hi> and <hi>Panigra,</hi> and did them ſome damage by the often ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Mines, and chiefly that of <hi>Panigra.</hi> At this time Signior <hi>Giuſtiniano</hi> Commiſſary of the Victuals, with two other Officers, were kill'd by the blowing up of one of them, which wholly deſtroyed the Left-horn of <hi>Panigra:</hi> and another Mine blew up the Counterſcarp. Upon an exact view of all the Souldiers in the City, it was found that about 1500 had been killed ſince the Siege; but that there were ſtill above 10000 able men left to defend the place.</p>
            <p>Now the Grand Viſier being more intent then ever upon the taking of the City, gave order that materials for building Huts and Lodges convenient for the Souldiers, ſhould be brought to the Leaguer, intending to lye before the Town all the Winter; reſolving not to raiſe the Seige till he had either ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Town, or loſt his whole Army in the Attempt.</p>
            <p>And the Turks having made their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58480:24"/>proaches to the Half-moon of <hi>Mocenigo</hi> and the Fort <hi>Panigra,</hi> lodged themſelves in the Trenches thereof; and in a ſmall time ſprung ſeveral Mines under each Work, which took ſo effectually, that a wide breach was made in both places; and the ſame night they immediately made a deſperate aſſault, appearing in great numbers upon the breaches, diſtinguiſhed by ſome white upon their Armes: but the Beſieged being very well prepar'd to receive them, the Turks, after a ſmart fight, were forced by the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to give over the Attempt, with a great loſs of men, and ſome Colours. So that the Enemy being ſo conſtantly defeated in their deſigns upon the Out-works, have given over thoſe places, being much diſcouraged by their great loſſes. The Viſier therefore commanded the Pioneers to undermine the Town-ditch; which the Chriſtian Officers obſerving, by their Counter-mines within endeavoured to defeat them, and with great good ſucceſs met with one of their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries, which they abſolutely ruin'd, and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Turks therein that were imployed in that buſineſs. The <hi>Candiots</hi> about this time received a recruit of 2000 Souldiers, and 200000 Crowns for their encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:58480:25"/>
            <p>In <hi>September,</hi> the Grand Viſier finding that his Souldiers, eſpecially the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> were ready to break out into a mutiny, and threatned to leave the Siege, being impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent at the tediouſneſs thereof, reſolv'd to put things to a ſpeedy iſſue; and therefore commanded a general aſſault to be made, which was accordingly executed. The Turks did ſtorm the Breaches very furiouſly; but were reſiſted ſo valiantly by the Beſieged, that after a fierce and bloody diſpute, they gave over with the loſs of 7000 men: The Chriſtians loſs was alſo great, who had 1500 of their men ſlain; among whom were five Noblemen of <hi>Venice,</hi> who with great honour ſold their lives in a defenſive War againſt the Common Enemy of Chriſtianity. The Turks finding their labour fruitleſs, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their endeavours to lodge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the breaches of <hi>Panigra</hi> and <hi>Moce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigo;</hi> have ſince ſpent their time in fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Trenches between the Bulwarks of thoſe two Forts, to hinder all communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation between them; and to that purpoſe they had brought thither a great quantity of earth, though with conſiderable loſs and danger; and were in hopes to make a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to the left Angle of the Fort <hi>Panigra,</hi> where they had made the wideſt breach;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58480:25"/>but the Beſieged, to fruſtrate their deſignes, appear'd upon the breach with a party of ſelect Souldiers, and a certain number of Slaves taken out of the Gallies that rid then in the Harbour, who behav'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo couragiouſly, that the Enemy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated; and the Chriſtians in the interim caſt up ſo ſtrong a defence in that part of the breach, clearing all to the Trench, and throwing out the Earth they caſt in, that there was little encouragement for a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond attempt: beſides, they placed a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine over againſt the Breach, (which was the invention of Captain-General <hi>Moroſini</hi>) which was Muſquet-proof, and could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain 20 Souldiers; where they might ſafely manage their Arms to defend the Breach. Many Mines were daily ſprung, and one of the Chriſtians did notable execution, where by blowing up twelve Barrels of Powder, there happened a great ſlaughter among the Turks; and many of their bodies were thrown into the Trench.</p>
            <p>The Beſieged alſo made many ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sallies, and to their great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had receiv'd a ſupply of two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, with ſtore of all neceſſary Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, that arrived ſafe at <hi>Candia</hi> in their Convoy, which conſiſted of twelve Ships:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58480:26"/>This made them reſolve upon a general Sallie out of the City, which was perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with great loſs to the Turks. The Enemy being almoſt tyred out with the Siege (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> and <hi>Spahi</hi>) their Army bring reduced from 60000 to 20000, were reſolv'd to quit the Siege; yet the Viſier by his great diligence and large promiſes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades them ſtill to continue at the Siege, where they ſtill beat the Town vvith their Ordnance.</p>
            <p>But among other late adventures, in <hi>October,</hi> about four Gally-ſlaves, belonging to the Venetian, being imployed in one of the Out-vvorks, diſcovered about 100 Turks dravving near them in a Body; vvhereupon one of them, vvhoſe name vvas <hi>Breſſano,</hi> making himſelf Captain, encouraging his Companions, and taking ſuch vveapons as came next to hand, iſſued out upon the Turks vvith great reſolution; kill'd 30 of them in a very ſmall time, vvounded many of the reſt, and put them all to flight for their ſafety: <hi>Breſſano</hi> having in this Sally given a ſufficient teſtimony of his great courage, by killing 16 of them vvith his ovvn hand. The Captain-General at this very inſtant ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Walls, and obſerving all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, ſent for him, and commending him
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58480:26"/>his valour, rewarded him with a Gold-Chain, and the Command of a Company of Foot; being very liberal in beſtowing moneys upon the reſt of the Slaves, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolling them into a Company. Much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this time an <hi>Aga</hi> with four Turks fled into <hi>Candia,</hi> with a conſiderable ſum of money; and ten or twelve thouſand Turks had quitted the ſervice, being weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with expectation, and tir'd out with the Siege; which extreamly incenſed the Viſier; yet he gave order for the repair of the Fort of <hi>New Candia,</hi> which he at his firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down before the City had demoliſhed as altogether uſeleſs; being reſolv'd to ſpend the whole Winter in lying before the Town: and in order thereunto, ſent out ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral diſpatches into <hi>Egypt, Barbary,</hi> and all other places in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire; threatning the Baſſa's with ſevere and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent puniſhment, if not abſolutely and ſpeedily obey'd.</p>
            <p>The Grand Signior was now arriv'd at <hi>Morea</hi> in perſon, to haſten the tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of freſh forces, intending to ſummon together the whole ſtrength of his Empire, rather then deſert the Siege diſhonourably. Yet notwithſtanding the great loſſes of men, the tediouſneſs of the Siege, the fruſtrating
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58480:27"/>of their deſignes in their aſſaults above, and the ſucceſsleſſneſs of their Mines under ground, the impatience of the Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, maugre all diſcouragement what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, they ſtill engage in many warm diſputes, and endeavour to fill up the Trenches; but the Beſieged ſtill beat them off, and throw out what they caſt in: but the Chriſtian Officers lookt upon this as prejudicial, and time ill ſpent, ſeeing the Enemy from one of his Batteries planted upon the Counterſcarp, deſtroyed their Blinds, and laid them open to their Small-ſhot; therefore they reſolv'd to deſtroy the Battery, and imployed the Pioneers to that purpoſe, who ſprung a large Mine, which blew it up wholly, with a great number of Turks, burying all their Cannons in its ruines, together with the <hi>Muſtapha</hi> Baſſa, <hi>Beilerbeg</hi> of <hi>Anatolia,</hi> one of the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable perſons among them, and who chiefly advis'd the carrying on the Siege on that ſide of the City. Several other Mines were ſprung the day following on both ſides, by which the <hi>Panigra</hi> was totally deſtroy'd, and reduc'd to a heap of rubbiſh, though ſtill defended with infinite valour; the Chriſtians appearing in white Armor, to the terror of the Enemy. After this, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58480:27"/>made many Sallies, and in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat drew the Enemy over Mines which were prepar'd for them; and when the Chriſtians ſaw their opportunity, fir'd them with great execution, and in little time beat them to their ſecond Redoubt, returning with Arms and Baggage in all their Sallies. Yet the Turks by the approaches of their Galleries made their advances with great obſtinacy, ſpringing divers Mines upon the Trenches of the City, with great damage to the Paliſadoes of the <hi>Falsbray</hi> near ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning; but the Chriſtians, by their indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, placed new Paliſadoes on the <hi>Falsbray:</hi> The Turks ſtill working their Mines with all the ſubtilty imaginable; one whereof they ſprung, which was under the <hi>Half-moon</hi> at the right-hand of the <hi>Panigra,</hi> which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fill'd a part of the Trench near the Front of the Bulwark <hi>Bethlem</hi> with its ruines; of which the Turks were reſolv'd to make the beſt advantage they could, and that very night were making preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for a ſtorm; but there fell ſuch violent rain in the night, that they were forced to deſiſt. Afterwards they ſprung another Mine in the <hi>Graft,</hi> which removed many Paliſadoes, and endangered the perſon of the Marquiſs <hi>Villa.</hi> Another Mine of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58480:28"/>which was ready to ſpring, was hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily diſcovered by the Chriſtians, and the Powder remov'd: the Enemy afterwards, when they thought it convenient, fir'd the Train, being big with expectation of the iſſue; but they were ſet upon by a party of the Beſieged, who alſo gave fire to two Mines of their own near <hi>Mocenigo,</hi> and one of 35 Barrels of Powder, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd many Turks in the ruines, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered their Mines in thoſe places.</p>
            <p>Now the Garriſon having receiv'd a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſupply of freſh Souldiers and ſome Horſe, they made a reſolute Sally; and the Turks drawing up all their forces, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the diſpute two hours together; but they were at laſt beaten into their own Trenches, with great loſs of their chief Captains and Commanders, beſides private Souldiers; the Grand Viſier himſelf eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping not without great hazzard of his life, or impriſonment. The Turks Army being now reduced to 18000, were reſolv'd upon a <hi>dernier effort,</hi> and to make a general Sally; but were repuls'd with great ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>Now ſince the <hi>Turk</hi> had made ſeveral experiments of the valor of the <hi>Candiots,</hi> by Aſſaults and Skirmiſhes which prov'd unſucceſsful, he endeavour'd to obtain by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58480:28"/>ſtratagem what he could not do by force; to which end they ſhot ſeveral Arrows in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City, to which they had faſtned Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, both in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Italian,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd many Arguments to perſwade the Chriſtians to a ſurrender, bragging of their Supplies they ſuddenly expected, reſolving not to quit the Siege; menacing them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their refuſal, with all the extremities us'd by an incenſed Enemy.</p>
            <p>On the fifteenth of <hi>November,</hi> in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, the Grand Viſier diſcharged all his Cannon, which were ſeconded with five Volleys of Muſqueteers, three of them with Bullets, and two without; accompanied with great ſhouts, and ſetting up many Lights about the Camp; which made the Chriſtians jealous of ſome large Succours ſent them, or ſome extraordinary expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from their Mines: but they drew up their men, and commanded them to ſtand all night to their Arms; and in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they found it onely to be a Turkiſh Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domontado, a meer Artifice of the Grand Viſiers, by throwing out reports of Succours and Supplies, to raiſe the drooping ſpirits of the Souldiers.</p>
            <p>The ſixteenth of <hi>November,</hi> being the Anniverſary of St. <hi>Giuſtina,</hi> on which in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58480:29"/>the year 1570, the Chriſtians gain'd a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Victory againſt the Turks, was cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated by the Beſieged with as much true zeal and joy, as that of the Turks the day before was counterfeit and feigned. Some few days after, the Grand Signior ſent the Viſier a Veſt and Scimiter as a preſent; which he receiv'd, with ſome Moneys for the Souldiers pay, which made them repeat the like Triumphs throughout the whole Turkiſh Camp.</p>
            <p>After this, the Chriſtians made a large Mine without, the <hi>Raveline di Samo Spirito,</hi> divided into three parts, which they ſprung ſo proſperouſly, that it ruin'd their Redoubts and Lines, blew up their Bodies in the Air, and entomb'd others of them in its ruines; which was followed by a ſtout Sally, to the deſtruction of many Turks, and ſome Commanders of Eminencie. At which the Viſier was ſo much inrag'd, that he reſolv'd to win the Town, or loſt his life in the attempt; ſending to all his Baſſa's through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Grand Signiors Dominions, for all ſupplies of Proviſions they could poſſibly furniſh him withal.</p>
            <p>The Turks having gain'd the ruin'd Out-works of <hi>Panigra,</hi> advanced with their Mines and Galleries towards the great
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58480:29"/>Trench; but a conſiderable ſlaughter hapned among the Turks, by the frequent ſpringing of the Mines, and numerous Sallies that were daily made: but Signior <hi>Lorenzo Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſani,</hi> the Proveditor of <hi>Candia,</hi> was ſlain by one of their Morter-pieces; and that Noble Venetian <hi>Bertolo Piſani</hi> unfortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kill'd by a ſhot. Yet the rains falling ſo exceſſively upon them, the Grand Viſier, withdrew, leaving about 6000 men behind him to defend the Batteries, and other Works.</p>
            <p>Much about this time, Secretary <hi>Giavarina,</hi> Miniſter of State to the Venetians, who had continued ſome time in the Grand Viſiers Camp, lodged in the Tents of <hi>Caterzogolo,</hi> which was a place of bad air, died, and five or ſix of his Family; which might be occaſion'd by the Contagion that raged ſo violently among the Turks.</p>
            <p>The City was now in a good condition, by reaſon of their conſtant ſupplies from the Fleet; but the Turks endeavoured to make good their Poſt in the ruines of the Fort <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigra:</hi> and the Venetian General ordered a new Line to be drawn in the old Works, to the end that the Beſieged might be in a capacity to defend every part of the Town ſufficiently, if the Turks (according to their
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58480:30"/>menaces) ſhould imploy their whole power againſt <hi>Candia</hi> the next Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier being now retir'd with the major part of his Army into the Vale of <hi>Giofiro,</hi> the 6000 men that he left, ſtill employed themſelves about the defence of thoſe Poſts that they had in their poſſeſſion; the Beſieged minding, during this vacancy, the prepration of their Works, and clearing their Trenches: but the Viſier ſent ſome additional Forces, and plenty of Proviſions from the Walls, where the groſs of the Army retir'd, with expreſs orders to loſe no opportunity of gaining upon <hi>Candia;</hi> which ſo encouraged them, that about <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> they made frequent aſſaults, and were as frequently beaten off; but on St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens</hi> day there was a great diſpute; the Beſieged iſſuing out in white Arms, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great number of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>In <hi>January</hi> the Turks quitted all their Batteries before <hi>Candia</hi> but two, and ſent moſt of their Cannon into <hi>Candia Nuova:</hi> and at this time there dyed among them near 200 in a day of the Plague; which made the Viſier retire ino <hi>Canea,</hi> ſending his ſick and wounded Souldiers into <hi>Napoli di Malvaſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58480:30"/>
            <p>The Chriſtian General reſolving now upon a Sally, drew out a ſtrong party, fell upon the Enemies Redoubts, and put the Turks to their heels; with a great loſs of men on their part, and but forty of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged. Now the Baſſa of <hi>Morea,</hi> had raiſed a Body of 8000 Turks, who were ready to be imbarqued for <hi>Canea;</hi> but they in their way ſeeing 3000 Turks wounded; who were conveyed in Carts to ſeveral Hoſpitals in <hi>Morea,</hi> prepar'd for their reception; this ſight made ſo deep an impreſſion upon them, that they all quitted the ſervice, flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Mountains for ſafety, and leaving their Bag and Baggage behind them; declaring their unwillingneſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in ſuch deſperate ſervice, where an Army of 60000 that ſate down before <hi>Candia</hi> at firſt, was already reduc'd to 16000. But the Grand Signior reſolv'd to employ all his Forces, both by Sea and Land, for the carrying on of the War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Candia;</hi> and therefore diſpatched two Chiauces to <hi>Tunis,</hi> and ſome other parts of <hi>Barbary,</hi> to command all aſſiſtance of Shipping, that they could poſſibly afford him; but he receiv'd a cold and diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory anſwer, by way of excuſe.</p>
            <p>In <hi>February</hi> the Turks having receiv'd
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58480:31"/>ſome Supplies, renewed the Siege, and caſt up a large Fort at the <hi>Sabionera,</hi> and planted many pieces of Ordnance thereon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they played very hard upon the Port and Town, but with very inconſiderable damage.</p>
            <p>Towards the latter end of this Month, a Renegado that commanded a Body of two thouſand Turks, endeavoured to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize the Fort St. <hi>Andre;</hi> but the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs <hi>Villa</hi> having timely notice of their deſigne, ſent Colonel <hi>Motto</hi> with a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable number of able and reſolute men, who aſſaulted the Enemy ſo couragiously, that they ſlew 500 of them upon the place, put the reſt to the rout, and with a very ſmall loſs return'd with 50 heads to the Town. Now the City had receiv'd a conſiderable ſupply of men; and Captain <hi>Molino</hi> having made a diſcovery of five of the Turkiſh Gallies coming out of the <hi>Dardanelloes,</hi> having aboard them men and Ammunition for the Grand Viſier, chaſed them with his Squadron for ſome hours, and ſunk two of them, the other three run aground upon one of the Iſlands to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void him, where they were broken in pieces, but the men eſcaped.</p>
            <p>The Turks about this time got many
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58480:31"/>Ships together, with Supplies intended for <hi>Canea;</hi> but they underſtanding that the Chriſtians Fleet was cruiſing about thoſe Coaſts, were forced to flee into <hi>Rhodes</hi> for ſhelter, and there expect the opportunity of a ſafe paſſage. Yet notwithſtanding all theſe diſcouragements, they continued their Mines, and attempted to make a way through the <hi>Graft,</hi> that they might aſſault the Town with the leſs difficulty; but by the vigilancy of the Defendants, at this very time, two of the Galleries made near one of the Principal Bulwarks of the Town, were blown up by the Chriſtians Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines.</p>
            <p>The Grand Signior appear'd ſtill more active in, and intent upon the buſineſs of the Siege then ever, drawing up great numbers of men in all places, intending to make them in all 100000 ſtrong; and to employ 100 Gallies, and fifty other Ships of force in the Service, with a great ſupply of all neceſſaries to the effecting of ſuch a work.</p>
            <p>On the eighth of <hi>March,</hi> ſeven Venetian Gallies cruiſing in the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> were ſet upon in the night by twelve under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Durach Bey,</hi> a famous Corſaire; but ſome other Chriſtian Veſſels coming
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58480:32"/>opportunely to their aſſiſtance: the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral took ſeven of them, which he ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Port of <hi>Candia,</hi> ſunk three, ſo that there onely eſcap'd two, very much diſabled. In which Naval engagement the Chriſtians loſt 400 men, and among the reſt Signior <hi>Daniel Giuſtiniano</hi> the Pay-maſter; <hi>Foſcarini,</hi> one Captain of a Gally, and ſix other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers were wounded; but there fell of the Turks <hi>Durach Bey</hi> himſelf, and ſome other perſons of note, with a great number of men; four hundred and ten Priſoners were taken, and 1100 Chriſtians and upwards freed from Turkiſh ſervitude.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>April,</hi> 1668, <hi>Georgio Maria Vitali</hi> was by the Senate made Knight of the Order of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> for his ſervice againſt the Turks. Upon this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat, the Captain of the Armata ſent a <hi>Tartan</hi> from <hi>Candia</hi> to <hi>Venice,</hi> who arriv'd the 21 of <hi>April, S. N.</hi> being Sunday, and brought with him ſeveral Flags, and other Trophies of Victory, as a preſent to the Grand Duke: and upon the entry of theſe Prizes into the Port of <hi>Candia,</hi> where they had a very joyful reception, and were welcomed with the diſcharge of the Towns great Guns; General <hi>Villa</hi> obſerving the Turks idly gazing upon the Triumphs of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58480:32"/>ſallied out upon them unexpectedly, forcing them to flee into their Camp, and killing them on their own Redoubts; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning with 100 of their heads, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about; which with <hi>Durach Bey's,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Turkiſh Captains that were ſlain at Sea, were placed upon Poles round about the City-Walls, to the terror of the Turks, and confuſion of the Baſſa, who vvas ſeen in a raging humour to tear his Beard out of vexation, to ſee that he in his deſignes prov'd ſo unfortunate. Upon the arrival of this Nevvs, the Senators attended the Duke to congratulate for this ſucceſs; vvho vvith the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> and Spaniſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, that vvere then at <hi>Venice,</hi> vvith a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Train of the Nobility, advanced to the Church of St. <hi>Mark,</hi> vvhere they heard <hi>Te Deum</hi> ſung; and then vvent in proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is uſual upon ſuch ſolemn occaſions. This very Evening the Senate honoured General <hi>Moroſini</hi> vvith the dignity of Knighthood, and conferred ſeveral honours upon his Relations, appointing revvards to be diſtributed among ſuch perſons as had ſignalized themſelves by their eminent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in this Engagement.</p>
            <p>The Turks grevv novv dead-hearted at the late defeat of their Gallies, and the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58480:33"/>Sally made by the Marquiſs <hi>Villa;</hi> inſomuch, that the Grand Viſier took up a reſolution to make no farther progreſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Candia,</hi> till the expected ſuccours, promiſed him by the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Emperour, were ſafely arriv'd. Signior <hi>Moroſini</hi> being inform'd that the Turks had a great ſuccour intended for <hi>Canea,</hi> took the Sea with 25 of his beſt Gallies, ſome Galleaſſes and Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, to engage them, whoſe Fleet conſiſted of 100 Gallies, 60 Saiques, and 25 great round Ships laden with Proviſions; but General <hi>Moroſini,</hi> after a bloudy ſight of ten hours continuance, burnt, ſunk, and took a great many of them; and two of their principal Baſſa's became his Priſoners, with moſt of the chief Commanders. About this time alſo ſeveral Privateers of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, <hi>Malta,</hi> and other places, met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; who joyning their Forces in the Gulph of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> took twelve Saiques be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Turks, laden with Proviſions for <hi>Canea.</hi> The Senate having had infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation that a Greek diſcover'd the Grand Viſiers deſigne to ſurprize the Venetians Gallies, whereby they obtain'd ſo ſignal a Victory, ordered him a Penſion of fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ducats a Month, in lieu of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58480:33"/>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday, May</hi> the ſecond, <hi>S. N.</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Villa</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Venice,</hi> who had ſerved the Republique in <hi>Candia</hi> about two years, in obedience to the Commands of his Maſter the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and with the Senates permiſſion; leaving the <hi>Sieur des Marets</hi> to ſupply his place, till the arrival of <hi>Monſieur de St. Andre Montbrun,</hi> who is to ſucceed him in the General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Molino</hi> alſo met with five Turkiſh Veſſels coming from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> bound for <hi>Canea,</hi> with conſiderable ſupplies for the Viſier; but he ſunk two of them, and took the remaining three.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Spaar,</hi> a German, who was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by the Senate as General of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Forces in <hi>Candia,</hi> with a Penſion of 4000 Ducats, ſafely arriv'd at <hi>Candia,</hi> with a Company of Ships well furniſht with Men, Ammunition and Money; ſo that the Town was in as good condition at this time, as when they firſt laid Siege to her.</p>
            <p>In this Month of <hi>May,</hi> the City made two Sallies more upon the Turks, wherein they behav'd themſelves with incredible courage. And Signior <hi>Claudio Araſſi</hi> a Serjeant Major, with Signior <hi>Mutio Mattei</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58480:34"/>Major-General of the Eccleſiaſtical Forces, dyed in <hi>Candia</hi> of the Wounds they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd in that Engagement of the <hi>Beiler</hi>-Gallies. Now the Turks endeavour to work with their Mines under ground, but the Beſieged ſtill Counter-mine them.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier loſt two of his prime Engineers, and is in ſo bad a condition for want of neceſſary Proviſions, that his Souldiers daily flee from their Colours; yet he ſtill obſtinately plays with his great Guns, and by mining, attempts the everſion of the repair'd, or new-rais'd Fort of <hi>Panigra,</hi> and the <hi>Half-moon</hi> of <hi>Mocenigo,</hi> making his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches towards the Port of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> but to little purpoſe; for the Beſieged made a vigorous Sally upon them, as they lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Fort, making them quit the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubt they had raiſed with much prejudice, and carryed with them many Priſoners into the Town; who upon examination, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd that the Turkiſh Army did not exceed 18000 in number, and thoſe ill command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too; for moſt of their experienc'd Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Souldiers had loſt their lives; the Viſier ſtill expecting the promis'd Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies from the Sultan, and the Baſſa of <hi>Morea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Turks finding that they could no
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58480:34"/>ways advance themſelves by open Force, endeavour'd to perform their deſignes by Treachery; which was thus attempted: They had ſo far prevailed with two Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Fugitives, with large promiſes of larger rewards, that they did ingage to give their utmoſt aſſiſtance: One of them was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey himſelf into the City (whilſt the other remain'd as an Hoſtage in the Turkiſh Camp for ſecurity) which he did, and was to nail up ſome of the Cannons in one of the Forts, which the Turks were then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to Storm, upon a ſignal given: but he was diſcover'd before he could effect what he intended; and being threatned, made a full confeſſion of the whole matter: whereupon the Venetian Forces being drawn up, the appointed ſignal was given, and the Turks approach with cheerfulneſs, as to a certain Victory; but at length they found themſelves ſo briskly entertain'd, that they retir'd with a great loſs of men; whoſe deaths they reveng'd upon him they had in their Camp, whom they cruelly put to death; and the other receiv'd the due reward of his intended Treachery in the City.</p>
            <p>Thirteen Turkiſh Veſſels vvere met vvith by a Squadron of <hi>Malteſes,</hi> that vvere
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58480:35"/>bound with ſuccours for <hi>Candia,</hi> who took ſeven of them; but thoſe of <hi>Malta</hi> diſmiſt the Ships, finding they belong'd to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who were compell'd to that employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The Turks were now much diſheartned, and grew very cold in their Aſſaults; finding that their ſupplies came in ſlowly, contrary to their expectation; which ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated the Chriſtians, who iſſued out, and engaged: them in their own Works, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away ſeveral of their heads upon their Pikes: but the Viſier being lately affronted, was reſolv'd on a reſolute attempt upon the Town; and to that end, ſent for 6000 Sacks from <hi>Canea,</hi> which were to be filled with Earth, and other Materials, to fill up the Trenches, and make a paſſage for his men, that he might thereby become. Maſter of ſome nevv Poſt: but this deſigne ſoon ſhrunk to nothing; their Forces daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, and relief no vvays increaſing as vvas hoped; inſomuch, that above one hundred Turks fled lately to <hi>Candia,</hi> beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Paſs-ports to return into their ovvn Country.</p>
            <p>In <hi>June,</hi> the City vvas refurniſhed vvith ſtore of all Proviſions, by the arrival of their Convoys; and the Fort <hi>Panigra,</hi> upon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58480:35"/>vvhich the Turks, laſt Summer, had done the notableſt execution, vvas ſo repai'd, that it vvas better to endure their attempts then formerly. The Viſier had a recruit of five thouſand Janiſarics novv arriv'd in a tempeſtuous Seaſon, vvhen Admiral <hi>Moroſini</hi> vvas in the Harbour, or elſe 'tis probable he had met vvith them, and ſtopt their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended courſe; and ſome Saichs alſo, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding the care and vigilancy of the Venetian Generals, have privily by night conveyed themſelves from <hi>Morea</hi> into <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nea,</hi> being laden vvith Proviſions and Forces, vvhich moved the Viſier to ſome ſpeedy action; to vvhich purpoſe he raiſed a great Battery before the Fort St. <hi>Andre,</hi> and ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Cannon cloſely, and furiouſly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted the Out-works, but was bravely beaten off by the Defendants: the <hi>Sieur des Marets</hi> gave eminent proof of his valor in this Service; vvho though ſurrounded, and out-numbred by the Turks, made his vvay through the midſt of them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain'd the Tovvn, vvith the loſs of a Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, another Officer, and moſt of his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovvers; yet the Turks had no cauſe to boaſt, their ovvn loſs being more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>The Turks did now almoſt deſpair of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58480:36"/>reducing <hi>Candia;</hi> yet vvith all their ſtrength they aſſaulted it in ſeveral parts at once, vvith great cryes ſetting upon the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works of the Forts of St. <hi>Dennis,</hi> St. <hi>Andre,</hi> the <hi>Sabionera</hi> and <hi>Panigra;</hi> but vvere beaten off the three firſt with great ſlaughter: their chiefeſt and greateſt aſſault was made upon <hi>Panigra;</hi> where coming on ſo violently and numerouſly , they poſſeſſed themſelves of a ſmall Work without the Fort, and kept it all night: But the next morning Signior <hi>Carbonaro,</hi> an expert Souldier and Engineer, fell ſo vigorouſly upon them, with a party in white Armor, ſallying out by break of day, and ſo nobly engag'd them, that after three or four hours diſpute, they were diſlodged in ſpight of all aſſiſtance; but the Enemy ſprung a Mine at their departure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Work, which deſtroyed and hurt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the Beſieged, with Signior <hi>Carbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naro:</hi> But in this, and the precedent days action, the Enemy loſt above 1000 men; and ſince that, played with ſuch fury upon the Town, both with their Cannon and Small-ſhot, that the General <hi>Bernardo Nani</hi> was wounded in the head by one of the latter, of which he afterwards dyed; and ſome Souldiers were ſhot upon the Walls.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58480:36"/>
            <p>In this Month the Captain Baſſa being at Sea with forty Gallies, and five men of War of <hi>Barbary,</hi> met with Cavalier <hi>Georgio Maria Vitali,</hi> a Privateer of great renown; who not at all conſidering the vaſt diſparity and diſadvantage in the number and ſtrength both of Ships and Men , entertain'd them with infinite courage, and defended himſelf for the ſpace of thirty ſix hours againſt them; ſhattering many of, the Enemies Gallies, and deſtroying a multitude of their men; but in the end was himſelf unfortunately ſlain with a Cannon-ſhot, having of 500 men but ſix remaining; his Ship being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly torn, fell into the hands of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, with Goods and Money, to the value of two hundred thouſand Reals. During this engagement, which was maintain'd by the Gallies, the Men of War ſet upon Captain <hi>Sgara,</hi> who was in the <hi>Neptune,</hi> a Ship entertain'd upon the Publick Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, attended by a Pinck; the Ship after a reſolute reſiſtance was taken, and the Captain too Priſoner; but the little Pinck being nimble, did fortunately ſave her ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the twenty ſeventh, the Senate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fented Marquiſs <hi>Villa,</hi> who was then making preparations in order to his return
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58480:37"/>to <hi>Savoy,</hi> with a preſent valued at 6000 Ducats, in acknowledgement of the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſervices he did for the Republique in this Siege.</p>
            <p>And <hi>July</hi> the ſixteenth, <hi>S. N.</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs <hi>Villa</hi> went to take his leave of the College, and receiv'd a rich Baſon of Gold as a preſent from the Republique, on which was ingraven a grateful acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſignal Services he had done them.</p>
            <p>Now the Viſiers Army was ſomewhat increaſed, but not ſo much as was expected: the Captain Baſſa being nearly related to him, is very zealous to afford him all the aſſiſtance imaginable: they ſtill continue the Siege; notwithſtanding the Venetian Fleet hinders their ſupplies, ſo that there was ſo great a dearth among them, that a pound of ſalt-fleſh was ſold for 40 Aſpres, a pound of Biſcuit, or Bread, for 20; but <hi>Candia</hi> had plenty of all ſorts of Proviſions, by reaſon that the Chriſtian Privateers, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten reſorted to their Port, to ſell their prizes. Beſides, <hi>Monſieur de St. Andre Montbrun</hi> ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arriv'd at <hi>Candia</hi> (to ſupply the place of Marquiſs <hi>Villa</hi>) with a great number of ſtout Souldiers; who to render himſelf fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous by ſome enterpriſe upon the Enemy,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58480:37"/>made a reſolute Sally with a party upon the Turks that lay before the Fort <hi>Sabio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera,</hi> forcing them out of their Trenches with great loſs, and deſtroyed the Work they had caſt up againſt the Fort; and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Moroſini,</hi> the Proveditor <hi>Catarin Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naro</hi> (till the Senates farther order) in the place of <hi>Bernardo Nani,</hi> lately deceaſed. Still the Turks obſtinately continued the Siege, and ſpent much ſhot upon <hi>Sabionera, Bethlem</hi> and <hi>Panigra;</hi> and the Viſier or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered a general aſſault to be made, being inform'd by a Fugitive <hi>Greek,</hi> that the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians were too ſlenderly provided in their Forts, to meet with any ſtout oppoſition; but he found the contrary, for the Beſieged beat them into their own Line, with the loſs of ſome hundreds of their men. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Viſier cauſed the <hi>Greek</hi> to be immediately impal'd for his miſ-informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Chriſtians loſt ſome men in this attaque, and among the reſt <hi>Monſieur des Marets,</hi> a perſon of great courage was kill'd out-right; and <hi>Monſieur de St. Andre Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> receiv'd a ſlight hurt in the face by a ſtone.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday, July</hi> the twenty eighth, <hi>S.N.</hi> the Senate made choice of his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency <hi>Girolome Battaja,</hi> a perſon of prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58480:38"/>Valor, and great Conduct, to ſucceed the late <hi>Bernardo Nani</hi> in his command, as General of the Forces in <hi>Candia;</hi> who by Order from the Senate was then preparing to depart.</p>
            <p>Signior <hi>Aleſſandro Molino</hi> was made by the Senate Captain of the Venetian Fleet in the <hi>Levant,</hi> to ſucceed in the Dignity of <hi>Cenſor;</hi> and they alſo made choice of Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deo Moroſini</hi> to ſucceed him in the Fleet.</p>
            <p>The Turks had now given a furious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault to the City, which was continued a whole night; the chiefeſt force being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed againſt the Fort of <hi>Sabioneca;</hi> but were repuls'd with incredible valor. In this attempt they were thought to loſe 1500 men at leaſt; with ſeveral Officers of note: of the defendants, there dyed about 200, with whom Colonel <hi>Aldobrandi,</hi> a perſon of an undaunted ſpirit, loſt his life.</p>
            <p>In another Aſſault, ſoon after, the Enemy for ſome little time were poſſeſt of the <hi>Half-moon</hi> of St. <hi>Andre;</hi> but the Chriſtians having before undermin'd it, blew it up, with great deſtruction to the Turks.</p>
            <p>In the Port of <hi>Gira Petra,</hi> ten Turks men of War, belonging to <hi>Barbary,</hi> met with five of the Venetian Fleet; the <hi>Confidence,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58480:38"/>the three <hi>Kings,</hi> the <hi>Mary,</hi> the <hi>Contarino,</hi> and the <hi>Golden Palm,</hi> commanded by the <hi>Sieur de Lionne;</hi> and after a ſevere and ſmart fight, one of the Enemies Veſſels being grappled with the <hi>Contarino,</hi> they both ſunk to the bottom; and the Captain of the <hi>Mary</hi> ſeeing that he was altogether over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power'd, cloſed with another <hi>Barbary</hi> Ship of great ſtrength; but firing his powder, they both blew up together: the noiſe and roaring of the Cannon in this engagement, had call'd in three other Ships to their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; at whoſe appearance, the Enemy made away with all the Sail they had, though they were ſuperior both in number and ſtrength; yet they departed not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome evident marks of this ſharp en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter.</p>
            <p>The Turks now for ſeveral days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther play'd hard. upon the Fort <hi>Sabionera,</hi> with Cannon and Morter-pieces; and then made a vigorous aſſault, but were beaten off: and at this time, <hi>Monſieur St. Andre Montburn</hi> made a ſtout Sally upon them, in which about 2000 Turks were ſlain. Now had the Turks receiv'd a conſiderable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, which ſpirited the Viſier, and made him reſolve to hold out the Siege. But 800 Janiſaries that were become both unable
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58480:39"/>and unwilling to continue any longer in that ſervice, mutinyed, and deſerted the Siege; ſeeking for an opportunity to imbark them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for their own Country. As the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-General of the Chriſtians Fleet was riding about <hi>Suda</hi> with 15 Gallies, waiting the motion of the Turks Fleet, he receiv'd intelligence, that the Baſſa of <hi>Canea</hi> had for the ſupply of the Camp before <hi>Candia</hi> (not without the Grand Viſiers order) ſent 200 ſelect Turks out of that Garriſon, to convoy ſome Cattle, great and ſmall, to their Army: Upon this information, the Captain-General landed a ſtrong party of his, commanded by an experienced Officer, who lay cloſe in ambuſh ſomewhat beyond <hi>Picorna,</hi> where they were to paſs; and as they came marching, he fell ſuddenly in upon them, ſcattered them, kill'd ſome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place, and return'd to the Gallies with priſoners, and the whole Booty; ſo that the Cattle were, by the Generals or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, preſently ſent into <hi>Candia</hi> for their ſupply.</p>
            <p>Much about this time, <hi>Monſieur de St. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre Montbrun</hi> obſerving that the Turks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to confide in, and rely very much upon a ſmall Work they had rais'd near the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaretto,</hi> expecting thereby to annoy the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58480:39"/>Veſſels, as they paſſed to and fro in the Port; he with ſome hundreds in Boats fell upon the Turks by night, and forced them to quit the ſame, which was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately demoliſhed, according to his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>The Turks did murmur, and were very much diſcontented at the proceedings of the Viſier, having loſt before <hi>Candia</hi> above 80000 able Souldiers, and trifled away two years time without gaining any one conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Poſt: they generally affirming, that their Prophet could not be expected, in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to favour or aſſiſt them in a War, that with ſo little cauſe, and ſo great circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention and treachery, was at firſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Grand Viſier continued his Batteries againſt the Town for thirty ſix hours together, without the leaſt intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; in which aſſaults he loſt 8000 of his men; wherein the Beſieged receiv'd ſome loſs alſo, and a few Officers. At <hi>Santa Vemerando,</hi> the Turks rais'd a new Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which made the Chriſtians ſally out, and repulſe them with great damage, whereby they did alarm the whole Camp; inſomuch, that the Viſier himſelf came to their aſſiſtance.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58480:40"/>
            <p>In this month, <hi>Vincenzo Roſpiglioſi</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Popes Gallies arrived at <hi>Candia,</hi> to the great ſatisfaction and joy of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged; who was ſaluted at his arrival with all the Artillery, with Volleys of Small-ſhot from the Souldiers, and then treated very honourably by the Proveditor General: <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi> did diſtribute a very large ſum of money among the Souldiers, as a Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and gave ſeveral preſents to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers. The Chriſtians receiv'd ſupplies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which they ſtood in need of; and the Turks play'd conſtantly upon the Port with their Batteries, and had lodged themſelves upon the Walls of <hi>Candia.</hi> The Turkiſh Fleet riding near <hi>Canea,</hi> conſiſted of 100 Gallies and upwards; with thirteen <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary</hi> men of War, having found 3000 men at <hi>Gira Petra,</hi> and 6000 at <hi>Canea,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruit the Viſiers Army, which was very much impair'd by their frequent aſſaults, whereby the Beſieged had receiv'd very conſiderable damages; for they loſt ſeveral eminent Officers, particularly Colonel <hi>Portario</hi> a <hi>Siciliot,</hi> the Engineer <hi>Quadru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plano,</hi> Serjeant-Major-General <hi>Motto,</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Gamba,</hi> and the Marquiſs <hi>Carlotti.</hi> The Turks made ſeveral attempts upon the Fort <hi>Sabionera,</hi> in which they loſt in few
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58480:40"/>days 6000 men and better; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards turned the main Body of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the Fort St. <hi>Andre;</hi> and at the ſame time, to divert the Defendants, ſtorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed three or four other parts of the Town; but <hi>Monſieur St. Andre Montbrun</hi> was ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant, that after a long and ſharp conflict, the Turks were beaten off with great ſlaughter from all places.</p>
            <p>The Venetians had landed 1000 able Foot about this time, expecting daily greater ſuccours. Now the Turks divided their Army into two Bodies; and at the ſame time made two deſperate aſſaults upon the Forts of <hi>Sabionera</hi> and St. <hi>Andre,</hi> lying near the Sea; but herein they loſt great numbers of their men, and the <hi>Aga</hi> of the Janiſaries was carried off by them with a mortal wound; but by an unfortunate ſhot they kill'd Signior <hi>Andre Semitecolo</hi> and <hi>Grioni,</hi> belonging to the Beſieged. Now there ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd at <hi>Candia,</hi> the Convoy commanded by <hi>Giacomo Cornaro</hi> with Men and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and 500 able Souldiers from <hi>Terra Firma,</hi> having in all put a ſupply of above 3000 freſh men into <hi>Candia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Venetians being highly encouraged by theſe ſupplies and recruits, made a ſally upon the Turks that were placed before
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58480:41"/>the Fort St. <hi>Andre,</hi> and counterfeiting a flight, drew them upon a Mine near the Fort <hi>Panigra,</hi> where they made a halt, and blew up the Mine, deſtroying ſome hundreds of them.</p>
            <p>The Turks having now lodged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Ditches of <hi>Sabionera,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by a Mine to blow up part of the Courtin; but the execution fell upon their own people, doing little or no damage to the Works.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the twelfth of <hi>Septehiber, S.N.</hi> a Ship arriv'd at <hi>Venice</hi> from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, bringing in it the body of the lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceas'd General <hi>Bernardo Nani.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Beſieged made a ſally upon the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers that lay before <hi>Sabionera,</hi> beat them off of their Works, and carryed away with them ſix of their great Guns: upon which the Viſier drew off his Forces forty paces from their former Poſts. In one of the Turks aſſaults, Colonel <hi>Proſilio,</hi> the Governour <hi>Tadeo Moroſini,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Venturini,</hi> were all three kill'd with one Cannon-ſhot; and the Beſieged, in a ſally made upon the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, kill'd many of them, and retreated to the Town with ſome of their Baggage, but loſt about fifty men, and a Nephew to the Marquiſs <hi>Villa,</hi> with three other perſons of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58480:41"/>quality. The Turks made another aſſault, being hightned with the former ſucceſs; but were forced back with the loſs of 1200 men, which were left dead upon the place. Much about the ſame time that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy attempted the Fort St. <hi>Andre,</hi> the Beſieged ſallied out upon them, and killed many upon the place, taking ſome Sacks of wool, which the Enemy us'd to defend them from their ſhot, with ſome Swords and Arms, which they carryed into the Town. In theſe aſſaults, and the ſally at the <hi>Sabio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera,</hi> the Chriſtians loſt about ſixty men, among whom were the noble <hi>Marco Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo,</hi> Colonel <hi>Sala,</hi> one Engineer of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> and three Serjcants; among the wounded were theſe perſons of note, <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo Dona, Franciſco Balti, Santo Barbaro,</hi> and ſome others, whoſe names we could not learn; alſo the General <hi>Cattarin Cornaro</hi> was ſlightly bruiſed with a ſtone.</p>
            <p>On the third, fourth, fifth and ſixth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, the Turks repeated their Aſſaults up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Fort <hi>Sabionera,</hi> being moved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by a large Breach they had made, of twenty Venetian paces in breadth; and though great numbers of them fell, they with great obſtinacy purſued their deſigne, endeavouring to march over their dead, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58480:42"/>to advance their Standard on the breach; but they met with ſuch ſtrong oppoſition, that the Standard was broke in pieces, and they driven back with extraordinary, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. In this action the prodigious valour of a Gally-ſlave was very obſervable, who was found to have kill'd forty two of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy with his own hand in one day; which the Captain-General taking notice of, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly rewarded him, and made him at that inſtant Serjeant to a Company.</p>
            <p>On the thirteenth inſtant, the new Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Battaja</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Candia</hi> with 2000 Souldiers, which he put into the Town, with a great ſum of money and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition.</p>
            <p>About the latter end of his Month, the rains falling in ſuch abundant ſhowers, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed many of their Mines and Pioneers, and did them much miſchief.</p>
            <p>On the fourth of <hi>October,</hi> the General <hi>St. Andre Montbrun</hi> made a notable brisk ſally upon the Enemy, from the Fort of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre,</hi> beating the Turks out of their own Line, and poſſeſt themſelves of one of their Batteries, drawings off a Morter-piece, and intending to carry off their Cannon planted there; but the Turks coming ſuddenly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them with their whole ſtrength, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58480:42"/>them in that enterprize, ſo that it prov'd ineffectual; and they retreated into the Town: Signior <hi>Franciſco Battaglia,</hi> a Duke in <hi>Candia,</hi> and Brother to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of that name, as he was with his own hands drawing off one of the Turks Guns, was kill'd unluckily by a Musket-ſhot; but his body was carryed off in ſpight of all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, by the valor of <hi>Carlo Dona,</hi> and <hi>Pietro Badoar;</hi> beſides, eighty men were loſt in this ſervice, and ſeveral wounded; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, Signior <hi>Matteo Semitecolo</hi> was ſhot in the Arm: ſince this, a Fugitive from the Enemies Camp inform'd the Beſieged, that the Turks loſt in this action about 1200 Souldiers; and among them the <hi>Aga</hi> of the Janiſaries, the Grand Viſiers Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and two other eminent Commanders, and had 1500 wounded perſons; which ſo diſcouraged the Beſiegers, that many of the Janiſaries deſerted the ſervice, and fled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mountains near adjoyning: and farther, that 300 Janiſaries beſides had ſeized upon ſome ſmall Barks, and were put to Sea, being quite wearied with the length of the Siege, and the little ſucceſs of their enterprizes, reſolving to return home: and withal, that the Enemies Gallies had land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about 1000 Janiſaries, for the ſuccour
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58480:43"/>and reinforcement of their Army; which upon the ſtricteſt and moſt exact inquiry then made, notwithſtanding all their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies and recruits, did conſiſt onely of twenty thouſand men; among whom were judged to be at leaſt ſeven thouſand Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers.</p>
            <p>On the fifth of <hi>October,</hi> the Turks made three ſeveral aſſaults upon the Fort St.<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre;</hi> and that ſo furiouſly and obſtinately, that the Town was in very great danger of being utterly loſt: but in the end, the Defendants forced them off with the ſlaughter of three hundred men, and ſome Officers.</p>
            <p>The Beſieged, about this time, were very much dejected, at the ſudden departure of the <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Malta</hi> Squadron; by which means the Turks took an opportunity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce their Army with ſome thouſands of men; but the Marquiſs <hi>St. Andre Montbrun,</hi> upon the appearance of the French Succours, with a party of reſolute Germans that were lately arriv'd at <hi>Candia,</hi> made a ſtout Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beat the Enemy from their Poſts, and did great execution. In revenge of this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, the Turks the very next day made a general aſſault with 30000 men at once, carrying Wool-ſacks before them to keep
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:58480:43"/>off the Small-ſhot; which being perceiv'd by the Beſieged, they immediately drew their great Guns to the Breaches, leden with Caſe-ſhot, and pointed upon them; which ſo gall'd the Turks, that they were forced to retire: whereupon the Beſieged made another Aſſault upon them with great ſlaughter; inſomuch, that the Enemy loſt in theſe actions about 10000 men. <hi>Don Vincenzo Roſpiglioſi,</hi> General of the Popes Gallies, being a little before return'd from the ſervice of <hi>Candia,</hi> which highly incenſed his Holineſs, excus'd it by laying the fault upon the Duke <hi>De Ferrandina;</hi> who being negligent, and not coming up with the <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> and <hi>Sicilian</hi> Squadrons, which he Commanded, he was unwilling alone to expoſe the Popes Gallies to ſuch imminent danger.</p>
            <p>The Viſier at this time was very ſevere, having taken off the head of one of his Baſſa's, for making a fruitleſs aſſault with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order: the Turks fleeing daily from their Colours, and ſcattering themſelves in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of the Iſland, though he had us'd all means imaginable to induce them to return; but his ſeverity in putting them to death when return'd, made the reſt betake themſelves to the Mountains for ſecurity.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58480:44"/>The Grand Viſier deſpairing of ſucceſs, having receiv'd ſo many and ſo great loſſes by the repeated Sallies of the Beſieged, and being very much injur'd by the Autumn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rains, took up a reſolution to withdraw his Forces to <hi>New Candia;</hi> but the Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior being very much incenſed at his ill ſucceſs, threatned him with the loſs of his head, if he gave him not a better account of the Siege then hitherto he had done. His Holineſs being very active to aſſiſt the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diots</hi> againſt the Common Enemy of the Chriſtian World, gave the Senate his Bull to diſpoſe of ſome Monaſteries in their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, to the value of one Million of Crowns, which the Republique made uſe of.</p>
            <p>At the latter end of this Month, the new Venetian General of the Fleet, <hi>Tadeo Moro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſini</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Candia</hi> with ſtore of Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, Souldiers, Proviſions and Money; wherewith he diſcharged the Souldiers Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears, to their. great ſatisfaction. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they made frequent Sallies againſt the Turks to their damage; in one of which, <hi>Monſieur St. Andre Montbrun</hi> had a ſlight. wound in the ſhoulder by a Muſquet-ſhot. The <hi>Siſter,</hi> an able Veſſel, belonging to the Venetian Fleet, was attaquet by five men of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58480:44"/>War of <hi>Tripoli</hi> in her Voyage homewards from the <hi>Levant,</hi> who defended her ſelf for many hours very reſolutely; but the Captain finding that he was over-power'd and out-numbred, and ſo much diſabled that he could make no further oppoſition, blew up his Ship, and deſtroy'd great numbers of the Turks that were at that time boarding of him.</p>
            <p>In <hi>November,</hi> the Turks withdrew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from <hi>Sabionera;</hi> but ſtood ſtill with great obſtinacy before the Fort St. <hi>Andre,</hi> intending to advance upon the Shoar, and ſhut up the entry into the Haven; but the French ſuccours marching out in four divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, made a brisk Sally, being commanded by the Duke <hi>de Roannez</hi> (who was owned there by his ancient Title of <hi>de la Feuillade</hi>) with extraordinary ſlaughter of the Enemy. The Count <hi>Strafoldi,</hi> who arriv'd about this time at <hi>Palma Nuova</hi> from <hi>Venice,</hi> intending to direct his courſe for <hi>Candia,</hi> to Command a Regiment of the German Souldiers late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employ'd in that ſervice, was unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately drown'd, as he imbarked at <hi>Talia Vento,</hi> with eighteen men, by the folly of the Sea-men, the Bark being over-ſet. The Senate ordered, that a preſent of Gold Plate, valued at thirty eight Marks, ſhould be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58480:45"/>ſent to Cardinal <hi>Roſpiglioſi,</hi> as an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the ſenſe they have of his zeal to promote their intereſt. The Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier having receiv'd ſome ſuccours from the Captain Baſſa, was very much encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to continue the Siege, raiſing Terraſſes about his own Tent, and had taken 2000 of his ſtouteſt Souldiers, as a Guard to his perſon.</p>
            <p>General <hi>Moroſini</hi> about this time diſpatched Colonel <hi>Machierotti,</hi> a <hi>Candiot,</hi> with Letters to the Viſier, deſiring him to accept of an exchange for Signior <hi>Laſcaris</hi> General <hi>de Bataille,</hi> formerly taken Priſoner; who went in a <hi>Felucca</hi> with a white Flag before <hi>Giofiro;</hi> but receiv'd this ſhort anſwer from the Viſier, That he came thither to take the City , and not to treat about Priſoners: whereupon Cavalier <hi>Grimani</hi> was imployed in the vacant charge.</p>
            <p>The Turks continue the Siege with great eagerneſs, notwithſtanding their numerous and ſignal defeats, and the vaſt inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Winter-Seaſon; and preſs ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhrewdly upon the <hi>Baſtion</hi> of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> playing upon it with their Cannon; by one of which the <hi>Sieur du Prc,</hi> Major to the Brigade belonging to the Count <hi>de St. Paul,</hi> had his head taken off; and the <hi>Sieur de
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58480:45"/>Chamilly</hi> and <hi>Lare,</hi> was hurt with the ſtones beaten out of the Parapet by the ſame ſhot; the <hi>Sieur de Marianval</hi> of the ſame Brigade was ſlain; the <hi>Chevalier de Merinville</hi> wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Granado; and the <hi>Sieur de Sablo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere</hi> hurt with an Arrow. The Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior being willing to ſupply the Viſier, as much as was poſſible, commanded 6000 men to be levyed out of the neighbouring places, ſending them to <hi>Salonica;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Captains could ſhip them, they rais'd a mutiny, and betook themſelves to their heels, to avoid the ſervice.</p>
            <p>On the twenty-eighth of <hi>November,</hi> the ſuccours from <hi>Malta</hi> arriv'd ſafe at <hi>Candia,</hi> and were nobly receiv'd by the Generaliſſimo, and the Marquiſs <hi>St. Andre Montbrun,</hi> who was then recover'd of his hurt he lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; but the Duke <hi>de Roannez</hi> was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſpleas'd, he being diſappointed of his hopes of commanding them.</p>
            <p>Now a party of 350 French Volunteers, with 50 more of the Garriſon, ſallied out upon the Enemy; but the former loſt thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen of their number, and the others three; but they kill'd ſome of the Enemy, brought off four of the Turks heads: and the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral made another Sally with ſixty choice men, who cleared the Trenches, killing fifty
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:58480:46"/>time, with the aſſiſtance of two Chriſtian Privateers, took five Saiques off of <hi>Canea,</hi> laden with Proviſions and Ammunition, intending for that Port; and in the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſixty Turks were ſlain, with their Captain a Renegado of <hi>Calabria,</hi> and fifty four Priſoners taken, who were put to the Chain, and the Proviſions ſent into <hi>Candia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pope now ordered preparations to be made by his Chamber, for the honourable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terment of the Marquiſs <hi>Villa,</hi> Commander of the Popes Forces, in the Church of St. <hi>Maries</hi> the great, who was kill'd in a Sally by a Cannon-ſhot, with the ſame Funeral State and Pomp that was made for Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior <hi>Mutio Mattei,</hi> who had the ſame Charge, and dyed in the ſame Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The Grand Viſier having intelligence that the French Forces were re-imbarqued, and homewards bound, made a furious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault, in the night, upon the Bulwarks of the <hi>Sabionera</hi> and St. <hi>Andre,</hi> at the ſame time, with 4000 men at each place, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately diſputed with the Beſieged for two hours ſpace; but they were forced to retreat to their Poſts, leaving the ground covered with their dead, and carrying off many that were wounded: the Chriſtians loſing not
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58480:46"/>above forty men in this ſervice.</p>
            <p>About the latter end of <hi>February,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>March, Moroſini</hi> the Captain-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral or Admiral of the Armata landed at <hi>Candia</hi> with 2000 able Souldies from <hi>Zante,</hi> 1700 Barrels of Powder, and a great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Proviſions arid Ammunition.</p>
            <p>The three Regiments of <hi>Lunenburghers,</hi> conſiſting of 2500 ſtout, well-diſciplin'd men, were in <hi>March</hi> imbarqued for <hi>Candia,</hi> being very well ſatisfied with their noble reception at <hi>Venice;</hi> the Senate beſtowing gold Chains upon their Officers, and a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat apiece was given to the Souldiers as a Donative. About this time, the Chriſtians ſprung a Mine , and fired it, by the which was deſtroyed a great number of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, with a Turkiſh Engineer, who was in great repute among them, and whoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections they obſerv'd in all their attempts. The Viſier, to revenge his death, and the loſs of his men, ſprung a Mine too; but it had not that effect which was expected: and then the Turks, by his command, attempted the Bulwarks of St. <hi>Andre</hi> with Ladders; but they were beaten off with great loſs, and many of their Ladders were by force drawn up from them into the Town. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Popes requeſt, his Imperial Majeſty
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58480:47"/>granted him 3000 men for the ſuccour of <hi>Candia,</hi> who were privately liſted without beat of Drum, out of the Imperial Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Countries onely.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday, March</hi> 30, 1669, <hi>S. N.</hi> the noble <hi>Giacomo Cornaro</hi> was choſen Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veditor General of the Armata, and Signior <hi>Pietro Diedo</hi> an experienc'd Senator, as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of a Convoy of many Ships laden with all manner of Proviſions, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo were many Souldiers, Chyrurgeons, Gunners and Labourers to be imployed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Works, and in the Mines. Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Giovanni Battiſta Zano</hi> endeavouring to take a Gallery from the Turks near <hi>Santo Spirito,</hi> was buried in one of their Mines; but the General ſent out a ſtrong party, who beat off the Turks, and recovered his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy out of the ruines of the Mines, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried it into the Town: Signior <hi>Pietro Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> by reaſon of his extraordinary indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Body, was upon his requeſt excuſed from his Voyage into the <hi>Levant;</hi> and the Senate made choice of Cavalier <hi>Zozzi Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naro</hi> in his room.</p>
            <p>In <hi>April</hi> 1669, the Turks made three deſperate aſſaults upon the Town, but were in all of them beaten off; and the Beſieged by the ſucceſsful firing of one of their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58480:47"/>Mines, totally ruin'd the Enemies Mount and Battery rais'd before the Fort St. <hi>Andre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Month the Grand Signior ſent a Baſſa to the Viſier, who in his name con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Viſier for the little advantage he had made in the Siege, trifling away three years time, with an expence of ſo much Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and the loſs of ſuch numbers of men, as might ſuffice for the Conqueſt of intire Kingdoms. The Viſier being very much diſatisfied with this meſſage, gave a furious aſſault to the Bulwark of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> and <hi>Ravelin di Santo Spirito;</hi> but the Turks af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an hours hot diſpute drew off; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 5000 of them hoping to paſs over one of the Mines of the Beſieged of 150 Barrels of Powder, it was fired, and blew up 3000 of the Enemy, wounding and diſordering them; and taking hold of this advantage, made a ſally upon the Beſiegers, and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Town with 1000 Priſoners, or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday, May</hi> the twenty ſixth, <hi>S.N.</hi> the Holy Sacrament was in St. <hi>Marks</hi> Church in <hi>Venice,</hi> pablickly and ſolemnly expos'd and on the <hi>Tueſday</hi> following, the Duke, Senate, and the greateſt part of the Nobility went in Proceſſion; publick Prayers
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58480:48"/>being made in all Churches, to crave a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the ſuccours and ſupplies intended to be ſent to <hi>Candia</hi> by the Republique.</p>
            <p>Now the Grand Viſier being very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of the Chriſtian ſuccours from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts, was reſolv'd to make a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral aſſault on the Forts of <hi>Sabionera,</hi> St. <hi>Andre,</hi> and <hi>Santo Spirito,</hi> ordering his Army (which notwithſtanding his recruits, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but of 24000) into three Bodies, to be imployed againſt thoſe three places; and for the better expedition of his deſigne, did from ſeveral Batteries play for ſeveral days upon the Town, and principally upon the Jews quarter; upon which they had done ſome execution; but he altered his minde, as to the general aſſault for the preſent, and call'd a Council of War, being reſolv'd, if poſſible, to oblige the Town to a ſurrender, before the arrival of the Chriſtian ſupplies: and in order hereunto,</p>
            <p>On the tenth of <hi>May,</hi> two hours before break of day, the Turks, according to their uſual cuſtom, fell upon the Bulwarks of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionera</hi> with great noiſe and fury, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a bloudy diſpute of three hours continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, the Chriſtians ſpringing ſeveral Mines, forced them to a rude and diſorderly retreat, leaving ſeveral ſcaling Ladders behind them;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58480:48"/>and they loſt in 'this ſervice three Baſſa's , with ſeveral other eminent Officers, beſides a great number of men.</p>
            <p>And about this time, the Venetian Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-General of the Armata, having receiv'd intelligence, that there were eighteen men of War belonging to <hi>Barbary,</hi> enter'd into the Grand Signiors Service for that Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and were ſet out from ſeveral parts of <hi>Alexandria, Smyrna,</hi> and <hi>Soria,</hi> laden with Men, Ammunition and Proviſions, bound for <hi>Canea,</hi> divided twenty four Men of War, under his Command, into three Squadrons, with orders to ingage the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, if diſcovered. The Admiral himſelf ſailing to the Eaſtward of <hi>Candia</hi> with ten Ships, where he diſcovered them, making all the Sail imaginable for <hi>Canea,</hi> whom he immediately fell upon, without any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their number, and a ſmart diſpute was entertain'd for ſome time; but the noiſe of the Guns brought in another Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of eight Venetian Ships to his aſſiſtance, ſo that in a ſhort time the Enemy was worſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſix Veſſels ſunk, and four taken, the reſt making away from him very much torn, and in great diſorder: beſides the number kill'd in that engagement, they took 800 Turks Priſoners.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:58480:49"/>
            <p>The Beſiegers, notwithſtanding all theſe ill ſucceſſes, continued on Shore, preſſing the City on all parts, plying it with their Batteries and Granadoes, eſpecially on the ſide of the Fort St. <hi>Andre,</hi> where his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency Signior Cavalier <hi>Cattarin Cornaro,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veditor extraordinary of the Armata, was kill'd unhappily by a Granado, which wounded him in the flanck, who receiv'd the Sacrament, and dyed an hour after.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Monday, June</hi> the ſeventeenth, <hi>S. N.</hi> the Senate made Election of his Excellency Signior <hi>Alviſe Mocenigo,</hi> to ſucceed in the place of the deceaſed Cavalier <hi>Cornaro,</hi> and conferred the Dignity of Knighthood upon his Brother Signior <hi>Girolamo Cornaro,</hi> in teſtimony of the high eſteem they had to the party ſlain, ordering a ſolemn Funeral to be celebrated for him upon the publick account, and a ſtately Tomb to be erected to his memory.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday, June</hi> the twenty ſecond, there arriv'd at <hi>Venice</hi> a Ship from <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> with the Body of the late deceaſed Proveditor extraordinary, Cavalier <hi>Cattarin Cornaro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Venetians had now received ſeveral Recruits, under the Command of Signior <hi>Priuli,</hi> as well as the Turks; who with
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58480:49"/>ſomuch aſſiduity continued their Batteries, Storms and Mines , that they made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of the moſt part of the Fort, &amp; planted there a Battery of ten pieces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, intending to play upon the Retrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Chriſtians , with the which they diſmounted ſeveral of the Defendants Cannon, and did great execution in the Town. In theſe late actions, Signior <hi>Gia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>como Contarini</hi> receiv'd a very dangerous wound in the Arm; Colonel <hi>Pini,</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd Officer was kill'd; and <hi>Monſieur de St. Andre</hi> had a ſlight hurt in the Arm, by the breaking of a Granado.</p>
            <p>The French Succours put to Sea in <hi>June,</hi> and arriv'd at <hi>Candia</hi> in his moſt Chriſtian Majeſties Fleet, commanded by the Duke <hi>de Beaufort;</hi> the Land-Forces being under the Command of the Duke <hi>de Navailles.</hi> And the Duke <hi>de Beaufort</hi> went in perſon to viſit the City of <hi>Candia,</hi> who was receiv'd with the diſcharge of all their Artillery, and with great acclamations; who taking a view of the Enemies poſture, receiv'd a ſlight wound by a Hand-Granado.</p>
            <p>About this time one <hi>Andrea Borazzi</hi> flee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Enemy, profer'd his ſervice to the Viſier, promiſing to inform him which were the weakeſt parts of the Town; who
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58480:50"/>was ſent accordingly with ſome Turkiſh Officers; but he leading them to an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie near the Walls, that they might the better ſurvey the Town, the beſieged fired a Mine under him, which blew up the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, he onely eſcaping: but the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier commanded him at his return to be put in Irons, ſuſpecting his deſigne to be a meer piece of Treachery.</p>
            <p>Still the Turks employed their whole ſtrength againſt the Bulwark St. <hi>Andre,</hi> and made a conſiderable Breach in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment; but the Chriſtians oppos'd them undauntedly, and repair'd by night what they beat down by day; and ſprung a Mine of 150 Barrels of Powder under the Enemies Battery upon the ruines of the Baſtion, which blew up a great number of the Turks, and four of their Guns: but the Beſieged loſt a perſon of great Reſolution and Conduct, the Noble <hi>Pietro Querini,</hi> by a Bomb, which breaking, gave another Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer a mortal wound: the Captain-General (who flood between them, obſerving the Enemies) remaining untoucht. The Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan upon advice of the arrival of the French ſupplies, propoſed terms of peace, as he had formerly done oftentimes, onely to amuſe them, he being abſolutely averſe to any
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58480:50"/>ſuch thing in reality, and to gain upon them the better by ſuch fair propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>The Turks now had by their frequent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults and mines, made themſelves Maſters of the ruin'd Baſtion of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> except a part of an Orillon , which was ſtill in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute. But the General with a party of flout men made a ſally upon the Turks; who not being able to ſtand in oppoſition with them, quitted their Poſts: This vacant time the Beſieged ſpent in caſting up a ſmall Defence there, which kept the Enemy at a farther diſtance.</p>
            <p>Now that the French Forces were arriv'd, and the Duke <hi>de Navailles</hi> had conſulted with the Captain-General; the Turks were advanced, and had taken up their Poſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Baſtions of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> and <hi>la Sabio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera:</hi> upon this Conſultation with the French and Venetian Officers, it was thought very proper to attaque them upon the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionera;</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Navailles,</hi> the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Forces, deſir'd to have thoſe Souldiers out of the Garriſon, that could be well ſpar'd; which they condeſcended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: and farther, order was, given for five or ſix hundred Pioneers, to be imployed in throwing down the Works made by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58480:51"/>and a Sally to be made at the ſame time, to divert them from ſending relief to the other ſide. The Duke <hi>de Beaufort</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be an unactive ſpectator, offer'd them 1500 men out of the Fleet, and put himſelf in the head of the French Forces, being ready to receive Orders from the General, though very much urg'd to the contrary. And thus he entred upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the twenty fourth, firſt 400 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded men marched out, and 50 others with Granadoes at the head of them; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them three Troops of Horſe, under the command of <hi>Monſieur Dampier;</hi> then the Regiments of <hi>Gaures, St. Valier, Lorrain</hi> and <hi>Bretagne</hi> followed, with four Troops of Horſe upon the Wings, beſides a party of the French Kings Muſqueteers, and 100 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Officers placed between the firſt and ſecond Line, to be ready upon any occaſion. The Forces that came from the Fleet were at the ſame time to fall upon the left-ſide of the <hi>Sabionera;</hi> and <hi>Monſieur Marſhal</hi> of the Camp appointed to aſſiſt them. In this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they marched ſilently and undiſcover'd, and drew up in Battalia, in a little plain near the Enemies Camp: the commanded men coming within Muſquet-ſhot, were
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58480:51"/>fired at by the Turks; and then <hi>Monſieur de Dampier</hi> was commanded by the General to fall upon two Redoubts in the head of their Quarters, being aſſiſted by ſome of the Guards; which was ſo couragiouſly and ſucceſsfully managed, that they took them immediately, and put every men to the Sword; and then their Lines were entred, and the Regiments of <hi>St. Valier</hi> and <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> poſſeſt them: the commanded men with the Companies of Guards, beat the Enemy out of their Trenches and Works. Thus far their deſignes proſpered, though they had but 300 of the 1500 expected from the Ships; nor were any Venetian Forces nor Pioneers ſent out to their aſſiſtance, as was promiſed.</p>
            <p>The Turks having thus deſerted the Camp, drew up into a Body, upon a riſing, on their right-hand; which being obſerv'd by the General, he in the head of his Forces marched towards them, and beat them twice from their Station; but he charged them ſo home upon the third rally, that he gain'd the place whereon they firſt drew up their men. Then hapned a croſs accident that ruin'd that whole days deſignes; for ſome Powder, Morter-pieces and Granadoes, taking fire by chance upon a Battery which
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58480:52"/>the Guards were poſſeſt with, they forſook the place in diſorder and confuſion, though <hi>Monſieur Caſtellan</hi> uſed all art imaginable to bring them back; and the 300 men that came from the Navy, fell into the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, notwithſtanding all the endeavours of the Commanders to rally them. This made the Turks begin a freſh charge; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Admiral, <hi>Monſieur Colbert,</hi> and the fifty Muſqueteers, joyned with the firſt Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion, and manfully oppoſed them; but this accident had imprinted ſuch a general terrour upon the Souldiers, that they were oblig'd to retreat; which was much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd by a Courtin, made good by the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. The Body of Reſerves was inveſted by ſeveral Forces, which after a ſlight skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh at the Baſtion of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> were ſent to aſſiſt their fellow-Souldiers at the <hi>Sabio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera;</hi> who alſo retreated diſorderly at laſt. The General gave ſignal teſtimonies of his Courage and Conduct in this days diſaſter; and made good his Retreat, paſſing through a party of the Enemy, with three or four Gentlemen onely that aſſiſted him; but if all things had been performed as was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, this day might, in all probability, have put an end to the Siege. The Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians had in all 600 men which were kill'd
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:58480:52"/>and diſabled. A Trooper eſcaped from the purſuit of the Enemy, found the Duke <hi>de Beaufort</hi> ſo wounded, that he had not ſtrength to get up behind him; and he drew him a while by the Arm, thinking to bring him off; but being ſo cloſely followed by the Turks, that he was compel'd to flee, he left him to the Enemy, who kill'd him preſently upon the place.</p>
            <p>Yet the next day, being the twenty fifth of <hi>June,</hi> about 200 of the French made a Sally out of the Baſtion of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> which gave ſuch an Alarm to the Turks, that they came to make good their Poſts; but the Beſieged firing three Mines, blew up many of the Beſiegers, with ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of Quality; and deſtroyed a very conſiderable Battery.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July</hi> the fifth, <hi>S. N.</hi> the Count <hi>de Vivonne</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Candia</hi> with the French Gallies, who took poſſeſſion of the charge of Admiral, finding the Fleet deſtitute of one. The ſame day alſo arriv'd the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of <hi>Malta</hi> Gallies with eight hundred Souldiers.</p>
            <p>On the ſixth, the Duke <hi>de Navailles,</hi> being over-heated in the late engagement, fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a violent Fever.</p>
            <p>On the twelfth of <hi>July,</hi> arriv'd a Convoy
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58480:53"/>at <hi>Candia</hi> with 1600 Souldiers, Ammuniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Monies.</p>
            <p>The Baron <hi>de St. Marre,</hi> Captain of the Guards to the Duke <hi>de Beaufort,</hi> hearing as yet no news of his Maſter by Spies, or any other means whatſoever, went in perſon to the Viſier's Camp; where being admitted by him into the Tent, he gave him a view of all the Heads that were cut off in the late fight; but he could not finde the Admirals among them; at which the Viſier was very much diſſatisfied, and afterwards gave him liberty to diſcourſe with ſeveral Priſoners in the Camp, but he could learn no news of him that was ſatisfactory.</p>
            <p>On the twenty fourth inſtant, all the <hi>French, Malta</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi>'s Squadrons were ordered to lye before the Turks Poſt at St. <hi>Andre,</hi> where they fir'd upon the Enemies Camp, and did them great damage: but when the Generals had drawn out their Forces, and were ready to fall upon the Beſiegers, the <hi>Tereſe,</hi> which was the French Vice Admiral, blew up by ſome unfortunate accident, or a ſhot from the Enemy, with 400 men aboard, to the damage of ſeveral Veſſels, the Admiral particularly, that lay next her, and the Captains Gally that took fire alſo, but was quenched; which made
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58480:53"/>the whole Fleet put out to Sea, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the Generals deſigne of making a Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but the Turks receiv'd great hurt by the firing of the Fleet; and loſt an <hi>Aga,</hi> the Viſiers great favourite.</p>
            <p>On the thirtieth inſtant, a Sally was made by <hi>Monſieur Colbert</hi> at the <hi>Sabionera,</hi> with ſome execution upon the Enemy; but <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Colbert</hi> was ſlightly hurt in the head with a ſtone which fell from the Gate, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a Morter-piece.</p>
            <p>The General <hi>Girolamo Battaja</hi> was mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded, in three places, by a Morter-piece breaking near him, which was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd from the Enemies Batteries, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then buſied about the <hi>Sabionera,</hi> and giving Orders to his Officers againſt ſome freſh approach intended by the Beſiegers. The Turks continue ſtill imploying their greateſt force againſt St. <hi>Andre,</hi> having raiſed a Battery, and planted eight Guns there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firing upon the Retrenchments made by the Beſieged, to ſupply the ruines of that Fort; but were valiantly oppos'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puls'd: however, the Enemy took an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Poſt near the <hi>Scozzeſe;</hi> which made Signior <hi>Navaglier,</hi> a Noble Venetian, ſally out with a party of Souldiers, intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to diſlodge them; but he received a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58480:54"/>dangerous Muſquet-ſhot in the neck. The Turks ſtill plyed the Town with ſhowers of Stones, Morter-pieces and Granadoes; and Count <hi>Waldeck</hi> General of the <hi>Brunſwick</hi> Forces, was kill'd with one of them. The Beſiegers then endeavouring to bend their ſtrength towards the <hi>Arſenal,</hi> on the ſide of the <hi>Sabionera,</hi> met with ſuch oppoſition, that they gave over that attempt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted their Forces to the other ſide of the Town, where they made themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the firſt Retrenchment, not without great loſs; and did attaque the ſecond; but the Beſieged had caſt up two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Works behind them, with large Trenches.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Anguſt,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mirandola</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Candia,</hi> and landed his Ammunition with 1400 of his own men, and 600 others, and Monies for the Souldiers.</p>
            <p>The Turks had now caſt up a great Mount upon the ruines of the Baſtion of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> and planted ſeveral Cannon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, with which they greatly annoyed the Town; but to fruſtrate this deſigne, the General cauſed the Church of St. <hi>Frances</hi> to be fill'd with Earth, and drew twenty great Guns upon it, which played hotly upon the Enemy, diſmounted their Cannon,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58480:54"/>and made the place altogether uſeleſs.</p>
            <p>The Turks ſtill laboured hard to take in the ſecond Retrenchment; but the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants fir'd a Mine made under that Bulwark, which being divided into ſeveral Branches, kill'd many of the Enemies, deſtroyed part of their Works, whoſe ruines divided 400 Turks from the reſt of the Body, ſo that they could not poſſibly eſcape, but were all taken priſoners, and carryed into the Town: and the Beſieged made another ſucceſsful Sally, upon the firing of another Mine, with an incredible ſlaughter to the Turks, and brought off with them a conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Priſoners. Then the Turks on the other ſide of the Town, endeavour'd to ſhut up a Sally-port near the <hi>Sabionera,</hi> that ſo they might make a farther progreſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sea, and by degrees attempt the <hi>Arſenal;</hi> but by a Sally in favour of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Mines, they left off that enterpriſe with loſs.</p>
            <p>Now the Auxiliary Forces ſent from <hi>France</hi> were imbarqued, being in all 88 Sail, in order to their return. Upon whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, the Turks took courage, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately fell upon the <hi>Sabionera,</hi> and St. <hi>Andre,</hi> with two great parties, thinking the Beſieged were diſpirited, and quite diſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58480:55"/>the French Fleet being gone; but they found the contrary to their detriment, loſing 3000 men, after three fierce aſſaults; and the Defendants but 200, with ſeveral that were wounded; who by firing of a Mine of thirty Barrels of powder under the Bulwark, where the Enemy had raiſed a Battery which much infeſted the ſecond Retrenchment, that was wholly deſtroyed, and the Turks in great numbers either blown up, or buryed in the rubbiſh of the Battery.</p>
            <p>The Generaliſſimo at length, finding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their Sallies, Aſſaults, Mines and Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes, that <hi>Candia</hi> was reduced to a meer heap of Rubbiſh, being ſo far entred by the Turks, and the Garriſon ſo leſſened, that there remain'd in it no more then 3600 men fit for Service, ſo that it was thought ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely impoſſible to preſerve it any longer from the Enemy, call'd a Council, where it was reſolv'd <hi>nemine contradicente,</hi> that they ſhould uſe their utmoſt endeavours in order to a Treaty with the Viſier about a Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and accordingly Colonel <hi>Arnardi,</hi> and Signior <hi>Scordeli</hi> the Vice-Chancellor, were employ'd to manage the Treaty; and on the firſt of <hi>September,</hi> were ſent out to the Poſt on the ſide of <hi>Giofiro</hi> with a white
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58480:55"/>Flag, whoſe buſineſs was communicated to the Grand Viſier: The news was immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſpread throughout the whole Turkiſh Camp, and entertain'd with exceſs of joy, and Commiſſioners appointed to treat on the Turks behalf; between whom that whole day was ſpent, with no other iſſue, but that the next conference ſhould be in the open Field, before the Fort <hi>Demetrius,</hi> where the Turks ſet up a large Tent for that purpoſe; where the Treaty was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till the fifth of <hi>September,</hi> and then the Articles were concluded upon by both parties; for performance whereof they gave Hoſtages on both ſides, particularly Signior <hi>Calbo</hi> Commiſſary for Proviſions, <hi>De Riva</hi> Lieutenant of the General Guards, and <hi>Zaccaria Mocenigo,</hi> from the Venetians; and the <hi>Beglerbey</hi> of <hi>Temiſwar, Mahomet Baſſa,</hi> the <hi>Aga</hi> of the <hi>Janiſaries,</hi> and <hi>Gaſſi Bey,</hi> the <hi>Tefferdat</hi> of <hi>Romilia,</hi> from the Turks.</p>
            <p>The Turks Hoſtages were ſent into <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> and the Venetians into the Turkiſh Camp, where they had an extraordinary civil reception, there being a rich Apartment pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for them, a Guard of Janiſaries or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to attend them whither they pleas'd, and a Table of thirty Diſhes of meat al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="articles">
                        <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                           <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="110" facs="tcp:58480:56"/>
                        <p>
                           <hi>their Arms and Baggage. That he permit the Inhabitants, who have no deſire to continue there, to retire with their Families, Kings and Jewels, whither they pleaſe. That he conſent, that the Captain-General may carry away all the Republiques Sacred Veſſels, and all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments whatſoever belonging to their Churches.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Seventhly, that the Captain-General may take out of the City of</hi> Candia 320 <hi>Braſs Guns, which are to be in the power, and at the free diſpoſal of the moſt Serene Republique of</hi> Venice.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Eighthly, that the Priſoners and Slaves taken on both ſides, during the Siege of</hi> Candia, <hi>be immediately reſtor'd; the Captain-General and the Grand Viſier having already given out their Orders requir'd for the execution of this Article.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ninthly, that all theſe Articles agreed and faithfully executed, both parties ſhall ſwear and promiſe to preſerve the Peace reciprocally, and inviolably, for the advantage of the Trade, and the mutual quiet of both their Subject.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>On <hi>Friday,</hi> the twentieth of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the Garriſon marched out without the leaſt diſturbance; the Viſier being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58480:56"/>to be rendred as famous for his juſtice in performing Articles, as for his vigilancy and courage in War.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> the thirteenth, a ſtately Hearſe was expos'd to publick view in St. <hi>Marks</hi> Church, and the Church it ſelf hung with Black, and fill'd with many Lights, in cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Funeral of his Excellency Signior Cavalier <hi>Cornaro,</hi> where a ſolemn Maſs, and variety of excellent Muſick, was perform'd by ſeveral Quires; and in the cloſe, Father <hi>Coſmi</hi> pronounced a Funeral-Oration, wherein was an account of all the eminent Services of that Illuſtrious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander.</p>
            <p>On the twenty ſecond inſtant, the Senate reſolving to confer the Dignity of Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of St. <hi>Mark</hi> upon Signior <hi>Franciſco Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſini,</hi> Captain-General in <hi>Candia;</hi> the great Council being aſſembled, the Election was made by a general ſuffrage; and the favour was the greater, in that there being then no vacancy, he was added a ſupernumerary.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Friday, September</hi> the twenty ſeventh, the Forces were drawn out of the City of <hi>Candia;</hi> and the ſame day, according to the Articles of Agreement, the Keys were ſent to the Viſier, who receiv'd them with many ſignes of joy, and rewarded the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58480:57"/>perſon that brought them with a large ſum of Money; whereupon he immediately ſent into the Town ſome of his people to cleanſe it, and take the dead bodies out of the four principal Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> St. <hi>Titus,</hi> St. <hi>Salvator,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter;</hi> about which work ſeveral days were ſpent. The Grand Viſier's civility was eminently mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to all the Venetians Officers of any note; but more remarkable to the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſimo <hi>Moroſini,</hi> to whom he gave ſeveral preſents, with this Complement, <hi>That the Peace ſhould be as long-liv'd as his Command;</hi> to whom the General return'd ſeveral pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents likewiſe.</p>
            <p>On the fourth of <hi>October,</hi> the Grand Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier made his ſolemn entry into the City of <hi>Candia,</hi> at the Breach of St. <hi>Andre,</hi> with all his Army, which conſiſted of about 15000 Souldiers, &amp; between ten &amp; eleven thouſand Pioneers; beſides other neceſſary Attendants. At his entrance, he found the City empty, without People, Goods or Proviſions; there being onely left behind two Greeks, three Jews, and eight more ſtrangers, whom the Viſier would alſo have ſent away; but they were of opinion, it was more convenient to change their Religion then City , and ſo turn'd Turk.</p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58480:57"/>
            <p>Since the Grand Viſier's entring into the City, he hath converted the four principal Churches thereof into Moſques, for the worſhip of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> and the other are turn'd into Stables, for his own, and the Horſes of his Souldiers.</p>
            <p>In this Month the Articles of Peace were ratified by the Grand Signior at <hi>Lariſſa;</hi> and on <hi>Monday, October</hi> the twenty one, <hi>S.N</hi> 1669, the French Ambaſſador made his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to the Venetian College, with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements of Condolency for the Surrender of <hi>Candia,</hi> and of Congratulation for the Honourable Articles of Peace concluded between the moſt Serene Republique and the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port; which were, the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening they came to their hands, being the eighteenth inſtant, ratified and confirm'd by the Votes of the whole Senate, three onely excepted; and the Ratification immediately diſpatched to their Captain-General.</p>
            <p>Since this, Signior Cavalier <hi>Molino</hi> was choſen Ambaſſador extraordinary to the Grand Signior, with an ample and firm Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification or the ſaid Peace, together with a noble and rich Preſent of Cloth of Gold to himſelf, and ſeveral conſiderable ſums of Monies, as Preſents to his Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:58480:58"/>
            <p>Now the Generaliſſimo <hi>Moroſini</hi> left the charge of the whole Army, with the Conduct of the Fleet which is to tranſport the Venetians, with all things neceſſary, to the care and management of <hi>Monſieur de St. Montbrun,</hi> who made ſome ſtay at <hi>Standia,</hi> he himſelf being gone to <hi>Suda,</hi> with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perſons of Quality, the Natives, a Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Ships, and a conſiderable quantity of Proviſions, and number of Men, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inforce that, and the reſt of the Garriſons that continue ſtill under the Juriſdiction of the Republique; and to furniſh them with all things convenient and neceſſary for their defence, upon all occaſions that ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen.</p>
            <p>The Viſier was now reſolv'd to remain at <hi>Candia,</hi> and to take up his Winter-Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters there, notwithſtanding the many ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations to return to the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Court, and the joyful entertainment and reception that he might rationally promiſe himſelf from the ſucceſs of this tedious and long Siege; excuſing his abſence, by repreſenting to the Sultan the neceſſity of his continuance in that Iſland, to ſettle his Conqueſt; but 'tis thought by ſome, that he was unwilling to intermeddle with the troubles of that Court, till he could ſee the iſſue of the affairs of the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58480:58"/>Sultaneſs; who hitherto had preſerv'd the lives of the Grand Signiors Brethren, by the aſſiſtance and help of the Janiſaries, that had eſpouſed her intereſt, and ingaged in her concerns.</p>
            <p>The Generaliſſimo <hi>Moroſini</hi> ſtill continued viſiting the Forts and Garriſons in St. <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and the Neighbouring Iſlands. Whilſt the Senate took all care imaginable for the diſpoſal of thoſe diſtreſſed Families, who upon the Surrender of <hi>Candia</hi> forſook their Habitations; and iſſued out Orders to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for their reception and maintenance in the Towns of <hi>Pola</hi> and <hi>Parenzo</hi> in <hi>Iſtria.</hi> The Archbiſhop of <hi>Candia</hi> having loſt his Benefice, obtain'd the Church of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> by his application to the Republique, in lieu thereof, and the Revenues thereof were to be ſetled upon him towards his ſupport, and the maintenance of the Dignity of that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; two of the Canons of which Church were diſpatched to <hi>Rome,</hi> to procure Power and Authority from his Holineſs, for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement thereof accordingly.</p>
            <p>Having thus given you a deſcription of <hi>Candia,</hi> in its Ancient and Modern Capacity, with an account of the beginning of the Siege in 1666, its continuance in the years
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58480:59"/>1667 and 1668, and Surrender in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of 1669 : We will cloſe all with this Obſervation, That it is a moſt prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thing, ſcarce to be parallel'd in Hiſtory, though it ought to be Regiſtred to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal honour of the Venetians, that an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable ſmall handful of men, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandihg all Attempts, Aſſaults, Mines, Countermines, Batteries, Martial-Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, and oppoſition whatſoever, both by open force, and private Treachery, ſhould be able to defend one ſingle City by Sea and Land, againſt the whole ſtrength of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, for the ſpace of one and twenty years together: which ſhould incite all Chriſtian Princes to imitate them in ſuch Noble and Heroick Actions, and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly to defend their Territories againſt the Sanguinary Turk, who is, and ever hath declar'd himſelf to be the Common Enemy of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:58480:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
